<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Englands condition parralelld with Iacobs for [brace] troubles. Salvations. Hopes. Laid open in two sermons, lately preached at Marlborough in Wilts. By Iohn Sedgwick, Batchelour in Divinity and Pastor of the Church at Alphage neere Cripplegate, London.</title>
            <author>Sedgwick, John, 1600 or 1601-1643.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 149 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92843</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2360</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E115_23</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18288</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860383</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860383</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112503</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92843)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112503)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 20:E115[23])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Englands condition parralelld with Iacobs for [brace] troubles. Salvations. Hopes. Laid open in two sermons, lately preached at Marlborough in Wilts. By Iohn Sedgwick, Batchelour in Divinity and Pastor of the Church at Alphage neere Cripplegate, London.</title>
                  <author>Sedgwick, John, 1600 or 1601-1643.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 42, [2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.B. for Samuell Gellibrand, at the Brazen Serpent in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "7ber 6".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Hosea II, 15 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Jeremiah XXX, 7 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112503:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ENGLANDS CONDITION PARRALELLD WITH IACOBS For</p>
            <list>
               <item>Troubles.</item>
               <item>Salvations.</item>
               <item>Hopes.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Laid open in two Sermons, lately preached at <hi>Marlborough</hi> in <hi>WILTS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Iohn Sedgwick,</hi> Batchelour in Divinity and Paſtor of the Church at <hi>Alphage</hi> neere Cripplegate, <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <bibl>MICAH 7. 8.</bibl>
            <q>Rejoyce not against mee O mine enemy, when I fall, I ſhall ariſe when I ſit in darkeneſſe, the Lord ſhall bee a light unto mee.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed by <hi>R. B.</hi> for <hi>Samuell Gellibrand,</hi> at the Brazen Serpent in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-Yard. 1642.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:112503:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:112503:2"/>
            <head>To the worſhipfull <hi>Philip Smith,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Franklyn</hi> Eſquiers, Members of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Houſe of Commons, now aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled in <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Encreaſe of Courage and Conſtancy of Spirit.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>SIRS,</hi> Thoſe who choſe you unto your places of great truſt and toyle might have justly (by nativeneſse of ſoyle, expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Love, and earneſtneſse of deſires) challenged the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication; yet they being many, and you their repreſentative body in an eminent and publike way, I hope it ſhall neither diſpleaſe them or trouble you, that the enſuing Sermons doe paſſe under your names to the publike view: I wiſh them in their printing their happie ſucceſſe in their preaching, they were words in ſeaſon to the beſt, and words of vexation to the worſt; Our miniſtry cannot pleaſe the one, but it muſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe the other; How ever its ſit, that every one have his portion; It is my comfort that by the happie ſucceſſe of the Goſpell in the hearts of the people, <hi>Marlborough</hi> is a Towne honouring and cleaving faſt to the <hi>Parliament;</hi> they choſe not Burgeſſes either to diſgrace or to deſert them; neither you nor they come under the cenſure of <hi>Solon's</hi> Law to the <hi>Athenians</hi> who adjudged him to die, and unworthy to live that in time of civill Garboyles (as careleſſe of the weale pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like) withdrew himſelfe, and became a Neuter: As you have not been drawne into unfaithfulneſſe by the ill examples of Revolters from their fidelity to their Country: ſo they have not beene betrayers of their owne liberties in joyning with any perſons (th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ugh great in place) in any illegall courſes of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion twixt King and people.</p>
            <p>If theſe Sermons had an influence on them, why may they
<pb facs="tcp:112503:3"/> not have an effect on you? The times are encreaſed in their troubles, the Cloud is growne blacker and bigger; ſome men are deſperate, others deſpaire, moſt ſee their dangers, few can believe and hope for deliverance: Out of my generall reſpect to the Times Lamentation, and for the raiſing up of yours, with other mens ſpirits, under our ſad conditions I have gathered up my ſcattered Meditations, which for ſubſtance are what I then delivered, though they have received their further additions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sirs,</hi> I will be no further troubleſome to my ſelfe or you: know; that the eyes of many are upon you, the prayers of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are for You, Nay there are more with you, then againſt you; as you have begun well, ſo end well, and the great God who is the King of Kings, even the ſupreame Iudge of all the world, hold up your ſpirits againſt all diſcouragements, and carry on your great works unto perfection, againſt all oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, giving unto you reward with himſelfe, ſo daily prayeth for you,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in the Faith, and Truth, John Sedgwicke.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:112503:3"/>
            <head>ENGLAND'S <hi>Troubles.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>JEREM. 30. ver. 7.</bibl>
               <q>Alas! for that day is great, ſo that none is like it, it is even the time of <hi>Jacobs</hi> trouble, but hee ſhall bee ſaved out of it.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Text (ſo ſuitable to our times) may not be unfitly reſembled to that <hi>Cloud</hi> by which God led the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> through the dreadfull and deſolate Wilderneſſe; as that, ſo this hath in it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>a darke ſide: viz.</hi> a diſmall time for trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and miſery, the face of the times gathered blackeneſſe; the cloud of trouble appeared, and calamities did ſo come on and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe that nothing elſe could bee found among the <hi>Iewes</hi> but troubles, great troubles even ſuch as no age could parallell, or fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going preſident equall: which makes the Prophet to cry out, <hi>Alas, for that day is great, ſo that none is like it, it is even the time of</hi> Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs <hi>trouble.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>A light ſide: viz.</hi> a gracious promiſe for ſalvation and deliverance, though for the preſent they were as men in graves and deeps under many pinchings and preſſures by miſeries yet a day and time ſhall come wherein the Lord would be light, and life and ſalvation unto them, <hi>but he ſhall be ſaved out of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might from the conjunction of the parts ſpend much time in opening this excellent truth.</p>
            <p>That out of the ſame mouth proceeds both threatnings and<note place="margin">Threatning of miſery, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of mercy conjoyned.</note> promiſes to the Churches of God; a Chriſtian hath but one
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:112503:4"/> GOD, though many conditions: and as God hath one heavie hand upon, ſo hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee another eaſing hand under his Churches; as hee ſtrikes, ſo hee ſtroakes them: as hee doth ſad, ſo hee doth cheare them; ſeldome or never ſhall you finde the Prophets in their meſſages to Gods people more terrible then comfortable; where they threaten miſery, they alſo promiſe mercy. The wiſe Phyſitian roles his bitter pill in ſugar; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> Now God doth ſweeten meſſages of miſery, with the openings of mercy; partly to make it knowne that in the midſt of wrath, hee doth remember mercy, and that in his ſtrict proceedings againſt his ſervants, hee ſits upon his throne of grace; what ever ſcourging rod God takes into his hand, and what ever in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ittering courſe God takes with his Children, hee is never of the Throne of grace, and the remembrance of his mercies: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> partly to teach that Chriſtians caſt downe outwardly, ſhould not deſpaire inwardly; God will not that miſerable times ſhould bee deſpairing times to his people: Though under ſenſible evills there will be the workings of feare, yet there ſhould be no ſinking of ſpirits; even in ſad times, faith muſt have its working, and the heart ought to be raized above the preſent ſe ſe of evill to an expectation of much good: the eye that ſees thoſe dangers which are upon the Seas, may behold the ſafeties which are in the harbors, God would have Chriſtians to know that they lie not at the mercy of any condition, and that when they are in miſery, they are under mercy; ſimply to bee threatned is a curſe, but to have a mingling of a promiſe with the threatning, argues both love from God and good to man; unto my underſtanding the bitter of all threatnings is taken off by the ſweet of a promiſe, and if God will vouchſafé to men a promiſe of delivery, they need not over feare the threatning Cloud of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery; its not the leaſt of a Chriſtians comforts, that as hee hath a threatning ſo he hath a promiſing God. This meditation I ſhall leave with you and betake my ſelfe to the words of my Text.</p>
            <p>In the darke ſide whereof we may take notice of theſe two things.</p>
            <p>1. The deep impreſſion which he troubles of the Church made upon the heart of the Prophet, laid downe in the word, <hi>alas!</hi> a word of ſorrow and compaſſion, all one in meaning, with woe is me! miſery hath befallen me! it doth even melt and mourn my
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:112503:4"/> heart within mee. I am a man undone to thinke of thoſe evills, which ſhall befall the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God. The ſpirit of pitie was not divided from the gift of propheſie; ô that we could be inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly afflicted! and greatly affected with the miſerableneſſe of our times! it is to bee feared that moſt men doe want ſympathizing and grieving ſpirits.</p>
            <p>2. The Rhetoricall expreſſions of the trouble: <hi>Troubles will make men Rhetoricall;</hi> The Prophet is full, and fit, high, and ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant in his openings of their ſad condition in and under their cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity. 1. He calls it <hi>a day,</hi> noting the manifeſtation and duration of the ſeaſon, which was alotted for their ſorrow and ſuffering: 2. It is <hi>that day,</hi> not an ordinary but a notable and remarkeable day, even a day anciently decreed, and frequently threatned. 3. It is <hi>great</hi> and that in reſpect of the wrath which ſhould be powred out, and in reſpect of the miſeries which were to bee endured, both, upon that day ſhould, for meaſure bee intended, and for length extended. 4. <hi>There is none like it;</hi> this phraſe ſets the day by<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Sorts of dayes. 1. Naturall. 2. Sinfull. 3. Sorrowfull.</note> it ſelfe, as having no fellow: Naturall dayes doe equall one anc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but ſinfull, and ſorrowfull dayes doe many times runne un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equally; though men may commit ſinne enough in one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay to make them eternally miſerable, yet one dayes wickedneſſe both materially and circumſtantially, may exceed all the reſt of a mans dayes; and though ſufficient to every day is the ſorrow thereof, yet ſome dayes of miſery may exceed all other dayes for bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; here is intimated unto us, that their miſery ſhould bee un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matchable by any foregoing preſident of miſery, if that they ſhould call to mind what they endured in times paſt, and compare it with the preſent ſuffering, it ſhould ſeeme as nothing, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they found it to be ſo: for the people under their captivity<note place="margin">Lam. 1. 17.</note> are brought in thus complaining, <hi>Is it nothing to you, all yet that paſſe by? behold and ſee, if there be any ſorrow like to my ſorrow, which is done unto mee, wherewith the Lord hath afflicted mee in the day of his fierce anger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>5. <hi>It is even the time of</hi> Jacobs <hi>trouble:</hi> whether we take the<note place="margin">A twoſold <hi>Iacob.</hi>
               </note> words perſonally for the man <hi>Iacob,</hi> or myſtically for the Nation of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> the ſeed of <hi>Jacob</hi> and the Church of God, wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not faile of the mind of God in the Text; It is true that <hi>Jacob</hi> in his owne perſon from the wombe to the tombe was a man of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:112503:5"/> troubles, himſelfe ſaith, <hi>few and evill have the dayes of the yeares of my life beene.</hi> And had the time of their captivity been filled up<note place="margin">Geneſis 47 9<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> with thoſe kinds of trouble wherewithall God exerciſed <hi>Iacob</hi> they ſhould have had miſery enough: and it is as true that the Churches and people of God wanted not their troubles when they were carried into captivity; troubles entred them into, and troubles continued with them under their captivity.</p>
            <p>There are theſe tenne things which will make evident unto us that the time of <hi>Jacobs</hi> captivity was a troublous time.<note place="margin">10 Things mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the time of <hi>Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aels</hi> Cap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ivity, a time of trouble</note>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, they were <hi>Warring and fighting times;</hi> it was a day of battell, a time of Sounding the Alarum, ſtriking up of Drummesand of arming one Nation againſt another: on came the <hi>Babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> and the <hi>Caldeans</hi> with a mighty Armie againſt the Nation<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Kings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4. 10, 11</note> of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and they did actually wage warre with them; Now we know that where God raiſeth up Warre, there the times muſt needs be full of trouble; it was ſaid of old <hi>Tubellum cauſa malo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> all evills are conceived in the wombe of War; alas! for the day of Warre, <hi>for in thoſe times there was no peace to him that went</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chro. 15. 5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>out, nor to him that came in; but great vexations were upon all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the Country, &amp;c.</hi> When coveteouſneſſe, pride, diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, malice, envie, and deſire of revenge ſhall bring in that unru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beaſt, <note n="*" place="margin">Bellum a b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a dictum: Silent le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges inter a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ma.</note> War, what can be expected but <note n="*" place="margin">R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> ſid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i castra seq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>tur.</note> that Lawes ſhould ceaſe, Religion it ſelfe bee laid aſide and all manner of villany bee committed.</p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, they were <hi>affrighting and trembling times;</hi> even times over-whelming and fainting the ſpirits of me and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men: I ſay that in the day of captivity the people were terribly ſhaken, God did <hi>appoint over t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>em t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rror as a judgement;</hi> Now<note place="margin">Levit 26. 16. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>their hearts did meditate terror:</hi> the noiſe without begat terror within, now their ſtout ſpirits did faile and faint, being as the heart of a Woman under her pangs; they ſtood ſhivering and<note place="margin">Ierem. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 22.</note> quaking before their miſery, and were encloſed with terror as was <hi>Paſhur</hi> who was terror round about; now trembling and fearing times muſt needs be troublous times.<note place="margin">Ierem. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, they were <hi>flying and purſuing times;</hi> the <hi>Jewes</hi> were as a Partridge hunted by the Fowler upon the mountaines. As they could not withſtand the ſtrength, ſo they could not endure the<note place="margin">Iamen. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſight of their enemies, <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> was made to hot for them, they
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:112503:5"/> were forced to leave their owne houſes, and their owne Country, and to flee from place to place, and knew not whither to betake themſelves for ſafety, the enemy did ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>agerly purſue them; now being in this flying poſture it could not but be a troublous time.</p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, they were <hi>ſcattering and dividing times;</hi> their cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity was their diſperſion; now husbands were divided from<note place="margin">Ierem. 40. 12.</note> their wives, fathers from their children, and one friend from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and knew not what was become one o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> another; one runs Eaſt, another runnes Weſt, a third North, a fourth South, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring up and downe, and it may be never ſeeing the faces each of other againe, this makes it a trouble in deed, when Husband and Wife, Father and Children ſhall be all under one roofe, and in one Towne and upon a ſudden (when they leaſt thinke thereof) to be parted one from another, and to bee no way helpefull one unto another, and it may be never to heare one of another.</p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fifthly, they were <hi>rebuking and ſcorning times:</hi> now <hi>Iacob</hi> lay under the reproachand contempt of the fooliſh. The children<note place="margin">Iob 30. 8, 9.</note> of fooles, and the children of baſe men that were viler then the earth made the <hi>Iewes</hi> their ſong and by word, <hi>ſuch as did ſit in the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalme 69. 12.</note> 
               <hi>gate ſpake againſt them and they were the ſong of the dru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kards</hi> the enemies laughed th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to ſcorne, and had them in deriſion all the day long; they abuſed them by word and geſtures and actions; O what gybing and jearing! What nodding of heads, making of faces, hiſſing of voyces, and clapping of hands was to be heard and ſeene among their enemies; the brethren tell <hi>Nehemiah</hi> that<note place="margin">Nehem. 1. 3.</note> they <hi>Were in great reproach,</hi> and the Hiſtory tells us; <hi>that all that paſſed by the way did clap their hands at them they did hiſſe and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lamen. 2. 15, 16<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note>
               <hi>wagge their heads upon the daughter Jeruſalem, ſaying is this the City that men call the perfection of beauty, and the joy of the whole earth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixthly, they were <hi>ſlaying and killing times;</hi> times of bloud and death, wherein multitudes loſt their lives by the ſword of the enemie, the very ſtreetes were filled with dead bodies, and the bloud of the <hi>Iewes</hi> was ſhed like water round about <hi>Ieruſalem, Pſal.</hi> 79. 2, 3. Now when the enemy enters with a drawne ſword caſting off all pity and mercy toward old and young, when they fall to cutting of throates, ripping up of bellies, ſtrangling, hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and the like, this makes it to be a time of trouble.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:112503:6"/>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Seventhly, they were <hi>wasting and ſpoiling times;</hi> even dayes of ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch deſtruction and deſolation, that Cities and houſes were conſumed with fire, Come trod under foot, Cattell conſumed and the whole land devoured and turned into a Wilderneſſe, marke the expreſſion; your Country is deſolate, your Cities are burnt<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ay 1. 7.</note> with fire, your land ſtrangers devoure it in your preſence, and it is deſolate as overthrowne by ſtrangers, and the daughter of <hi>Sion</hi> is left as a Cottage in a Vineyard, as a lodge in a Garden of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Cumbers, as a beſieged City.</p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Eightly, They were <hi>oppreſſing and evill e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>treating times,</hi> now things were not carried by right according to reaſon and the law of juſtice, but by might according to tyranny and injuſtice; the <hi>Iewes</hi> had wrong done to them, and they durſt not to complaine thereof, or if they made complaint they could find no redreſſe, the enemies were heavie handed, and cruell h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arted toward them, daily robbing and ſpoyling them, and did ſo weaken them that they made their lives tedious to them.</p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> Ninthly, They were <hi>ſpirit imbittering and ſoule ſadding times,</hi> even dayes of ſuch unquietneſſe, that they were bereft of all plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, they enjoyed not one merry day all the while they were in captivity, now <hi>their feaſts were turned into mourning, and all their ſongs into Lamentat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on, it was a bitter day</hi> as the Prophet threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, <hi>Amos</hi> 8. 10 the day was dark and cloudie wherein not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> the light of Gods countenance but all other outward and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward comforts were with drawne, it was night unto them, and the day was darke over them.</p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> Tenthly, They were <hi>treacherous and betraying times;</hi> their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies would ſometimes falſly accuſe and ſlander them giving out that they were rebels and traitors, anon the Lion would put on the Foxes skin, and pure enemies to their Religion would come in among them in ſheepes clothing; by and by they would be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring and confederating againſt them, alwayes they were plod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of further miſchiefe againſt them; ſo that where ever they were, and in what ever they did, they were laid waite for, which makes the time to be ſuch as the Prophet ſpeakes of.</p>
            <p>Now if to all theſe things wee doe eaſt our eyes upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving<note place="margin">Lamen. 1. 10.</note> of the Candleſticke, the denying them the free and pure uſe of the Ordinances, their beholding of their Idolatries and evill
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:112503:6"/> manners, this would make it to be the time of <hi>Iacobs</hi> trouble in a more ſpirituall way. Having given unto you this light into the Text, I come to the doctrinall reſult, which is this.</p>
            <q>That as the Churches and people of God may have their outwardly<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> 1. Gods Church have extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary troublous times.</note> peace full and prosperous times, ſo they m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, and oftentimes they have their wondrous troublous and miſerable times.</q>
            <p>It is with the Church for ſtate and condition below, as it is with the naturall day, each day hath a morning and an evening; or as it is with the revolution of the yeare; each yeare hath its Winter and Summer ſeaſons: Even ſo the Church hath; firſt, days and ſeaſons of grace, times of tranquillity and ſtability, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Candle of the Lord may ſo ſhine upon them, that they may enjoy many outward and inward comforts and content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, every man may ſit downe under his Vine and Fig-Tree, eate the fruit of his labours, and no man riſe up to make him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid: Next, dayes and times of miſery, called evill dayes, and in my Text, <hi>the time of trouble; the great day none like it;</hi> Time in<note place="margin">Troublous times what.</note> it ſelfe, and as it is a Creature is quiet, trouble is accidentall to it; now it is ſaid to be troublous, as peace is withdrawne from it and a Cloud of miſery drawne over it; when peace takes its leave, and diſorder or confuſion doth approach and appeare, this is that which makes time to be troublous and miſerable.</p>
            <p>Further you may note that there are two ſorts of troublous<note place="margin">Sorts of troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous times.</note> times which may befall the Churches and people of God.</p>
            <p n="1"> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Inward. </seg>1</label> 1. One <hi>inward,</hi> wherein Soule and Conſcience may lie un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der wounds and much diſquietneſſe; if God deſert and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw from <hi>David,</hi> now hee is troubled, <hi>Pſal</hi> 30. 7.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">Outward which is, 1. Perſonall. 2. Locall, or Nationall.</note> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Another outward wherein the body and ſtate of a man is under diſquietneſſe, or the Land and place wherein the Church is planted and placed is under miſery and affliction.</p>
            <p>I meane this ſort, and doe ſay that the Churches of GOD may meete with Land waſting, houſe burning, Women ravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing, Children killing, State devouring, Religion ſcorning, Ordinances caſting down, heart trembling, and liberties over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing times; in one word times may bee greatly miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and afflicting to them; and ſo full of ſadneſſe and confuſion,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:112503:7"/> that they may not know what to doe with themſelves, or which way to turne themſelves.</p>
            <p>That outward troublo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s times are of two ſorts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Ordinary</hi> and <hi>common,</hi> even ſuch as are uſuall, happening to all ſorts of peo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le in their times.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Extraordin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry</hi> and <hi>unuſuall,</hi> even ſuch as are extended and intended and cannot be equalled by any preſident, I ſay that ſore trou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le, great trouble, yea unmatcheable trouble may be the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Church and people of God.</p>
            <p>Further we doe not conceive troublous times only to bee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable and poſſible to the Churches, but actuall, it is not only true, that they may have troublous times, but it is alſo true that troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous times doe befall them: which truth hath.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The teſtimony of theſe Scrip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ures in one place it is ſaid, <hi>it is a day of trouble, and of ruine, and of perplexity, by the Lord of</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Hostes in the valley of viſion breaking downe the City and crying to the mountaines.</hi> In another place <hi>Hezekiah</hi> ſends the ſtate of the Church unto the Prophet in theſe words; <hi>This day is a day of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cap. 37. 3.</note> 
               <hi>and of rebuke, and blaſphemie for the Children are come to the birth and there is no ſtrength to bring forth:</hi> adde to this that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie of the miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ries of the Churches under the cruell perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Antiochus,</hi> when <hi>there was a time of trouble, ſuch as never was, ſince there began to be a Nation unto that ſame time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſtrength of theſe grounds; if any man will bee ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied in the cauſes of the Churches troubleous times, they are theſe:</p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> Firſt, <hi>Meritoriouſly</hi> troublous times doe ſpring from the<note place="margin">4. Cauſes of the Churches troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous times.</note> ſinnes of the Churches of God; as the needle drawes on the threed, ſo our ſinfull dayes being upon us our miſerable dayes; there is nothing which doth enter men into ſorrowes more than their ſins; ſin is the mother, and trouble the daughter; there had never been a bad day or ſad houre upon earth, had not man ſinned; this is the <hi>Achan</hi> that troubleth <hi>Iſrael;</hi> when <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſinned then<note place="margin">Pſalm. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8 32, 33</note> God conſumed their dayes in trouble, and brought them down: <hi>Ahab</hi> meeting <hi>Elijah,</hi> calls him the troubler of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet deales plainely and roundly with the King and tells him to his face that it was he and his Fathers houſe in forſaking the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements<note place="margin">1 Kings 18. 18.</note> of the Lord, and following <hi>Baalim</hi> that troubled
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:112503:7"/> 
               <hi>Iſrael:</hi> Hence is it that God ſaith, <hi>Make a Chaine, for the Land is full of bloudy crimes, the City is full of violence, wherefore I will bring the worst of the heathen, and they ſhall poſſeſſe their houſes, I</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 7. 23. 24, 25, 26, 27.</note> 
               <hi>will alſo make the pomp of the ſtrong to ceaſe, and their holy places ſhall be deſiled; deſtruction commeth and they ſhall ſeeke peace, and there ſhall be none; miſchiefe ſhall come upon miſchiefe, and rumor ſhall bee upon rumour—the King ſhall mourne, and the Prince ſhall be clothed with deſolation, and the hands of the people of the land ſhall be troubled, I will doe unto them after their way, and according to their deſerts will I judge them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſon </seg>2</label> Secondly, <hi>furtheringly</hi> troublous times do flow from the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant Party,</hi> Satan and his angels: Satan himſelfe is full of rage and malice againſt the Church; the glory thereof is his envie, and therefore he doth put out himſelfe in the power of the Dragon, and in the policie of the Serpent, to create what trouble hee can to the ſame; hee is the great kindle Coale; hee it was that ſtood at the right hand of <hi>Joſuah</hi> the High Prieſt ſtanding<note place="margin">Zech. 3. 1.</note> before the Angell of the Lord to reſiſt him: he it was that ſtood<note place="margin">Rev. 12. 4.</note> before the woman which was ready to bee delivered, for to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voure the Child as ſoone as it was borne; and hee is that <hi>Serp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt</hi>
               <note place="margin">ver. 15.</note> 
               <hi>which caſt out of his mouth wter as a floud after the woman that hee might cauſe her to be carried away of the floud:</hi> when Satan is let looſe, and hath his houre, he will ſet the whole world into combuſtion; Nay, wee have another <hi>Malignant party,</hi> who are<note place="margin">Rev. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the ſpirit and ſpawne of Satan; men of prophane hearts and lives, who doe act over the Devill, and worke that buſineſſe for him, which hee cannot worke for himſelfe; I am ſure where grace is wanting, and prophanneſſe raigning, there the ſpirit of ſpite and miſery of diſturbance is to bee found, men deſperately ſet on ſin have imbitterd ſpirits againſt the quiet of the Church, yea ſuch an enmity is there betweene the two ſeeds, that wicked men are alwayes bending their wits, laying their plots, and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out themſelves to diſturbe the quiet in the land; theſe are ſo ſet on ſire of hell, that they decline peace, and delight in bloud and Warre; <hi>Iſhmael</hi> like, they muſt have their hands againſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man, and <hi>Salamander</hi> like, they love to live and lie in the fire: Whence did all the tumults and uproares in <hi>Theſſalonica</hi> ariſe?<note place="margin">Acts 17. 5, 6.</note> did not the unbeleeving <hi>Jewes,</hi> who were moved with envie take
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:112503:8"/> unto them lewd fellowes of the baſer ſort, a company of vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonds and wicked fellowes! Theſe are fit inſtruments to trouble a Church and State, and Kingdome; I have obſerved that there are ſixe things in wicked men making them troublous to Gods people.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Their <hi>ignorance</hi> of the wayes and Religion of God: <hi>Theſe</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Things make wicked men to betroubl us. Ioh. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>things will they doe unto you for my names ſake becauſe they have not knowne him that ſent mee:</hi> And again, <hi>They ſhall put you out of the Synagogues, yea the time commeth that whoſoever killeth you will thinke that hee doth God ſervice, and theſe things will they doe</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 16. 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>unto you becauſe they have not knowne the Father nor me.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Your blackeſt clouds and darkeſt nights do foretell the greateſt ſtorms; and wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re ignorance and blindneſſe doth moſt poſſeſſe the mind, there is your grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt oppoſition againſt God and his cauſe; <hi>Paul</hi> was then a perſecutor when hee was under ignorance, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 13.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Their <hi>Pride</hi> of ſpirit; a ſpirit of pride is a ſpirit of contention, a proud heart will ſet Kingdomes on ſire; if <hi>Haman</hi> cannot get the knee from <hi>Mord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i,</hi> he wil deviſe a bloudy decree againſt the <hi>Iewes;</hi> if <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Domitian</hi> feare the looſing of their Crowns and Honours, they will command that all thoſe who are of the ſtocke of <hi>David</hi> in <hi>Iwry</hi> bee ſlaine; and if proud and accurſed Prelates bee put off their Cuſhions, and caſt out from honours, what miſchiefes will they not further? They will ſell themſelves to their ſhirts to recover their places; <hi>through pride commeth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Their exceeding <hi>Covetouſneſſe</hi> of heart; filthy luker and horrid cruelty are ſeldome disjoyned, when <hi>Demetrius</hi> and the crafts men ſaw, that the hope of their gaine was gone now they ſtirre againſt <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Sylas,</hi> and raiſe a mighty ſtorme in <hi>Macc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donia, Acts 16. 19, 20, 21, &amp;c.</hi> can you imagine that thoſe covetous wretches whoſe godlineſſe is their gaine, are idle at this day and doe not blow the Coale? Certainely Covetouſneſſe which is the Roote of all evill, muſt bee the cauſe of much trouble.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Their <hi>envious</hi> ſpirits; it was the ſpirit of envie in <hi>Caine</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Iohn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 12.</note> which made him to murther his brother <hi>Abel;</hi> and the <hi>Caldeans</hi> and Courtiers envying the advancement of <hi>Daniel</hi> and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:112503:8"/> his fellowes above themſelves, deviſed a meanes to deſtroy them, <hi>Dan</hi> 3. 8, 6, 3, 4.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Their <hi>proneneſſe unto Idolatry;</hi> heate is not more inſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſire then cruelty is unto idolatry; the love of Idols in all ages hath beene the Churches trou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le, what ſtickling was there at<note place="margin">Acts 19. 28. 34.</note> 
               <hi>Epheſus</hi> for <hi>Diana?</hi> and we know that <hi>Iezabels</hi> Idols diſturbed the kingdome of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Their <hi>contentedneſſe with formality in Religion,</hi> when men muſt have Religion in mans dreſſe, and are taken up more with formes of godlineſſe then the power of it, this makes the times to be troublous and perillous, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 1, 4, 5.</p>
            <p>Out of all this you ſee, that troublous times are from wicked men who never ceaſe from troubling untill they dye, theſe are<note place="margin">Iob 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7.</note> the <hi>earewigs</hi> and the biting <hi>Fleas</hi> ſtill troubling the ſtate of Gods people.</p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> Thirdly, <hi>inflictingly</hi> the Churches troublous times ariſe from the wrath of God let fall upon them; and his diſpleaſure concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved againſt them; when God is angry his Churches are troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; <hi>Thou hid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt thy face and I was troubled,</hi> and againe, <hi>by</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 30. 7.</note> 
               <hi>thy wrath are we troubled.</hi> This you know that a little fire cauſeth<note place="margin">90, 7.</note> a great deale of trouble, ſay that there bee but a finger burned or an Houſe on fire, doth it not occaſion a great deale of trouble and unquietneſſe? how much more ſhall Churches and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple bee diſquieted through the angry countenance of God?</p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>4</label> Fourthly, <hi>finally</hi> Churches have their troublous times for theſe ends and purpoſes!</p>
            <p n="1">1. For <hi>tryall and manifestation both of ſoundneſſe and of graces,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. Ends of the Churches trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles.</note> troublous times are trying times, it is not times of peace, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut times of Warre, which trieth the mettle of a Souldier, all the while the Ship lies on the ſhoare, or is in its harbour, its ſtrength to beare its burden is not knowne, but when its put out into the Sea, meetes with bluſtering ſtormes, and is toſſed and tumbled, if it now hold out, then its ſtrength is manifeſted; wee have many Trees with faire tops and make a goodly ſhew in calme ſeaſons, which topple downe in bluſtring weather, for want of firm roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the earth; the caſe is the ſame with men in the profeſſion of Religion. Multitudes ſeeme to be Religious, own the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and goe for Chriſtians in dayes of peace, who in more trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blous
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:112503:9"/> dayes will quit their ground, and forſake their Captaine, whereas now well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ooted and throughly ſanctified Chriſtians will keepe their ſtanding, and rather die then dem <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> grace in truth, will be grace in tryall, <hi>here is the faith and patience of the</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, q. d.</hi> if men have faith and patience indeed, troublous times will manifeſt it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>For the manifeſtation of wickedmen;</hi> their madneſſe and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignity of ſpirit would not appeare and be evideat unto men, and they would not ſhew themſelves in their colours, if there were no troublous times: in peacefull dayes enemies ſeem to be friends, and with the <hi>Viper</hi> they hide their teeth in their gummes, but when troubles appeare then they will ſpit out their venome mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the opportunitie for their dealing cruelly with Gods Saints.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>For the correction of abuſed peace,</hi> when Chriſtians do not well uſe their peacefull times God doth puniſh them with troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous times.</p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> In the firſt place we may informe our ſelves that outward du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable peace is no infallible note of a true viſible Church; the Church of God in Heaven is beyond all troubles, in Heaven there is full and laſting peace; but on earth, her condition is fluctuant with the <hi>Arke</hi> of <hi>Noah,</hi> and Militant as an Army that is in the field beſet with an enemy; having ſo many malicious enemies ſhe cannot be long quiet, and ſhee may better be diſcerned by laſting tryalls, and troubles then by conſtant peace; <hi>Gregory the great,</hi> ſpeaking of the Church ſaith, <hi>Eccleſiaeſt haeres orucis:</hi> the Church is heire to the Croſſe, and I would demand of papiſts what out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward peace had the Church in <hi>Aegypt</hi> under <hi>Pharaohs</hi> oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s? what peace had ſhe in her forty yeares travell thorough the Wilderneſſe, which was a place of temptations, journeyings, Warre, and many other ſtraites and inconveniencies? tell me ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly had ſhee not many encounters by enemies in the Land of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan?</hi> where was her outward durable peace whilſt ſhe was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der 70. yeares captivity in <hi>Babilon?</hi> and whilſt <hi>Antiochus Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanes</hi> did waſte and ſpoile her in her Ordinances and members? what meaneth the three hundred yeares perſecution by the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh <hi>Emperors?</hi> could theſe things happen to her, and yet is the true Church diſcernable by out ward and durable peace? by
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:112503:9"/> this very note we can diſprove <hi>Rome</hi> from being the true Church; for when <hi>Rome</hi> was burnt by the <hi>Goth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> ſackt by Charles Duke of <hi>Burbon</hi> in the dayes of Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the ſeventh, nay when their Popes were glad to flie and hide themſelves, yea were bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and impriſoned, where was the outward peace of that Church? Wee deny not but ſometimes outward peace may bee the portion of viſible Churches but that alwayes they have the ſame, only ignorance and impudencie muſt affirme.</p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, weeare not to wonder when we ſee the Churches of God caſt into troublous times; we have this day this Scripture<note place="margin">Times are and will be troublous upon foure occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</note> fulfilled; the times are troublous, the Lord in mercy looke upon us, yet let us not think it ſtrange, no new thing is hapned to us; let me tell you th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t upon foure occaſions times will be troublous.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">When Dagon is to goe downe.</note> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. <hi>When Dagon and Baal is to goe downe:</hi> no great and prevai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling evill can be hindred or caſt down without much trouble and tumult, if <hi>Gideon</hi> caſt downe the <hi>Altar</hi> of <hi>Baal</hi> and cut downe the grove by it, the men of the City keep a mighty ſtirre about it, the man they muſt have that did it; and die he muſt for it, or it ſhall coſt bloud, reade the Hiſtory, <hi>lud.</hi> 6. 28, 29. if the Goddeſſe <hi>Diana</hi> be in danger, what a noiſe and uproare is there in the City, they ſhout and make a hubbub, <hi>Acts</hi> 19. 28, 34.</p>
            <p>I conceive thus much, that <hi>England</hi> hath many bad tennants who having gotten poſſeſſion and can plead preſcr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ption (though no Scripture title) for themſelves are reſolved not to goe out without blowes and bloud; neither can it be imagined (unleſſe a miracle be wrought by God, as was in the caſe of the <hi>Scots</hi>) that ſo many proud Prelates, ſo many idle ſcandalous Non Reſidents, and ſo much Rubbiſh of humane invention crept into Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, will ever bee caſt downe or carried out without troubles; can you conceive tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Satan will looſe a Kingdom and never wag his taile; believe it, brethren; there are many thouſands in the Kingdom ſo ſet upon Idolatry, Superſtition and the wayes of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality that they cannot bee quiet if theſe things be taken from them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">When the Temple is to goe up.</note> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. <hi>when the temple is to bee reedified:</hi> No great and good worke can be carried on to perfection without much trouble; this is certaine that God hath brought us to Church reforming times and theſe alwayes have beene troublous times. The Angell ſaid
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:112503:10"/> to <hi>Daniel, the ſtreete and the Wall ſhall bee built in troublous</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>times.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <head>Out of which Text I note theſe two things.</head>
               <item>1. That when the Church begins to goe up, then troubles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to come on.</item>
               <item>2. That though troubles come on, the Church ſhall goe up.<note place="margin">The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Temple was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>I conceive that the times were very troublous when the City and the Temple was in building upon theſe eleven reaſons.</p>
            <p>Firſt, They were <hi>mocking and ſcorning times</hi> to the <hi>Iewes,</hi> as is plaine in theſe words, <hi>But when Sanballat the Horonite and To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biah the ſervant the Ammonite and Geſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m the Arabian heard it, they langhed us to ſcorne, Neh.</hi> 2. 19. Theſe fellowes fell a jearing the <hi>Iewes,</hi> thinking thereby to daſh the worke out of credit and the builders out of countenance.</p>
            <p>Secondly, They were <hi>falſe accuſing and ſlandering times</hi> to the <hi>Iewes:</hi> the enemies did not onely give it out among themſelves that they were Rebels and Traitors, but they did accuſe them to the King and their owne faces of Rebellion, and yet they were not able to prove the ſame as you may read, <hi>Ezra</hi> 4. from v. 6. to v. 16. and <hi>Neh. 2. 19. What is this thing that you doe; will ye rebell againſt the King?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, They were <hi>hindering and inhibiting times</hi> to the <hi>Iewes: The Lord Chancellor Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um, Secretarie Shimſai,</hi> and the reſt of their companions ſo farre prevailed with the over credulous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> that he gave command that they ſhould ceaſe buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and by this meanes there was a ſtand put unto the worke for many yeares, <hi>Ezra</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 17. to 22.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, they were <hi>inſinuating and diſſembling times</hi> to the <hi>Jewes,</hi> the pure enemies to the worke of building came unto them with tenders of their ſervice, as if they had beene willing to beare part of the charge and to doe ſome great work for the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding up of the Temple; let us (ſay they) build with you, for we ſeeke your God as you do, <hi>&amp;c. Ezra 4. 2. Neh.</hi> 6. 2.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, they were <hi>conſpiring and confederating times</hi> againſt the <hi>Iewes,</hi> now the enemies held a Councell, and called a convocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to ſee what was to be done to hinder them in this good work, and at laſt it was reſolved upon; that they ſhould try all their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>inds, ſend out into every County to gather together tag and rag
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:112503:10"/> and no man were he never ſo baſe and vile in condition that would come in and joyne with them ſhould be put by; as you may read <hi>Neh</hi> 4. 8.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, They were <hi>treacherous and betraying times</hi> to the <hi>Jewes;</hi> when their enemies ſaw that they could doe little harme to them whileſt they were a party united among themſelves, they practiſe a moſt perillous attempt, namely to divide; that ſo they might have a partie among them: and to this end they bribe <hi>Iuda,</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> certaine of the falſe hearted Nobles and ſuperſtitious Prophets, which became a diſgracefull ſnare to themſelves and a mighty hinderance to the worke: Now <hi>Nehemiah</hi> had much to doe to keepe up the hearts of the people and to hold them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for that great worke. Conſider, <hi>Iudah</hi> comes in thus playing his part: <hi>The ſtrength of the bearers of the burdens is decayed, and there is much Rubbiſh, ſo that we are not able to build the Wall, and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Neh 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.</note> 
               <hi>our adverſaries ſaid they ſhall not know n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r ſee till we come in the midst among them, and ſlay them, and cauſe the worke to ceaſe.</hi> Was not here a faire diſheartning tale w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> might eaſily take with ſuch whoſe ſpirits were lazie and fearefull, might not the lazie ones have thus reaſoned amongſt themſelves, I promiſe you theſe men ſpeake reaſon, this worketh maketh my ſhoulders to ake, I have carried out ſo many burdens already, and what a deale of carriage doth remaine yet; toile and moile who will, I will bee an <hi>Iſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar</hi> no longer, ſeeing I may have my eaſe and the Nobles like well of it I will accept it; worke who will worke for me, and if the Temple be not built up untill I further it, it ſhall never be built might not the fearefull ones have thus reaſoned, what ſhall we die and be ſlaine? build who will for me, <hi>Skin for skinne and all that a man hath will hee give for his life:</hi> joyne to this the carriage of the propheteſſe <hi>Noadiah,</hi> and <hi>Shemajah</hi> the ſon of <hi>Delajah,</hi> they<note place="margin">Neh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 12, 13</note> ſhut up themſelves and preach to the people, <hi>get into the houſe of God within the Temple, and ſhut the doores of the Temple, &amp;c.</hi> was not this a taking plot to have grave and learned men come in with their Counſells, caveats, and arguments? might not the <hi>Iewes</hi> have ſaid ſurely the danger is great, there cannot be all this ſmoake without ſome fire? come let us take warning in time and give off working, we have heard and ſeene the ſayings and doings of many of our Nobles, men great in birth and bloud
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:112503:11"/> and ſee which way they incline, but now the Prophets who are men inſpired of God they come with a warning from Heaven to us and if wee ſhall ſlight them alſo, ſhall wee not bee guilty of our owne death, if we ſhall continue in this worke of buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, they were <hi>oppoſing and withſtanding times</hi> to the <hi>Jewes:</hi> the enemies were not alwayes in deliberation and ſpeech but they proceeded to action, we read that <hi>Tatnai Shethar-Boſnai</hi> and their adherents came to the heades of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and did que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n them by what authority they did build up the Citie and<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> make up the Wall: and not contented with this they begin to raiſe an Army that they might come and fight againſt <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and with the utmoſt of their power they did ſet themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the building.</p>
            <p>Eightly, They were <hi>ſelfe deſending times to the Iewes; Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> was forced to divide the ſervants, halfe wrought in the worke, and the other halfe of them held both the ſpeares, the ſhield and the bowes and the <hi>Habergions:</hi> Nay the builders of<note place="margin">Neh. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 16. 17. 18, 21, 22, 23</note> the Wall, and the bearers of the burdens were but halfe handed, for in one hand they held the Trowell and in the other hand the Sword: further the <hi>Iewes</hi> were forced to their no ſmall trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and coſt to keepe a ſtrong guard about themſelves day and night.</p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> Ninthly, They were <hi>deſpiſing and undervaluing times;</hi> the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies in reproach of their work ſaid what doe theſe feeble <hi>Jewes?</hi> will they fortifie themſelves? will they ſacrifice? will they<note place="margin">Nehem. 4. 2.</note> make an end in a day, will they revive the ſtones out of the rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſh which are burnt? when the Army of <hi>Samaria</hi> had thus ſpoken, <hi>Tobiah</hi> the <hi>Ammonite</hi> makes his ſcoffing ſpeech. Saying, <hi>Even that which they build, if a Fox goe up hee ſhall even breake downe their ſtone wall:</hi> as if they ſhould have ſaid.</p>
            <p>What doe theſe ſilly and ſelfe deceiving men intend, doe they imagine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat they are conſiderable to goe forward with this great worke, they thinke to carry all cleare before them, that they ſhall meete with no adverſaries or that we will ſtand by as lookers on holding our hands; no ſuch matter, weele warrant them, they ſhall finde ſtout men among us, yea tenne for their one, who will oppoſe them. What do they imagine to have their old ſacrifices,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:112503:11"/> ſolemne dayes and aſſemblies, in this they are miſtaken; ſee how early they riſe, how luſtily they worke, and how late they leave off, as if all the building ſhould up, before any body heard of it; let them goe on the worke which they have taken in hand, they ſhall never be able to effect it. For we will hold their noſes to the grinſtone, and they ſhall find it to be another manner work to finiſh then they look for: ſee how theſe doating men are glewing the old ſtones together again, as for new ones where will they get them let them alone; ſuffer them to go on, ſee what they will do, and when they have done the moſt and the beſt that they can, they ſhall but build Caſtles in the ayre, yea ſo weake ſhall bee their worke, that if a Fox come up hee ſhall with his feete overturne all, we are ſure that wee can overthrow all at our plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> Tenthly, They were <hi>ſelfe juſtifying and clearing times:</hi> the <hi>Iewes</hi> were forced to bring out the Kings authority, and to ſhew <hi>quo warranto,</hi> they did enterprize the worke, wee read of many ſelfe acquitting Orations which were made by them, <hi>Ezra</hi> 5. They were forced to plead their owne loyalty to their Soveraigne and to teſtifie their owne innocency to the world.</p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> Laſtly, They were <hi>enemies anſwering times:</hi> Sometimes <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ballat</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nehem. 6. 21. verſe 2. to 9.</note> and <hi>Geſhem</hi> ſent meſſengers for meetings and conferences, they ſought by Parliances to hinder them from going on in their building, which when they could not obtaine (though requeſted foure times) then they fall to writing of letters, ſome of them containing unjuſt charges, other ſome expreſſing unreaſonable demands, all which tooke up much time in their reading and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering, which could not but be a great trouble to <hi>Nehemiah</hi> and very delaying to the worke.</p>
            <p>By theſe inſtances you ſee how heavily the good worke went on, and how juſtly I affirme that a Church can neither bee foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded or reformed, but the times will bee very troublous; if God bee caſting a Corner ſtone upon which hee intends to raiſe up a ſpirituall building, and if hee call together a company of labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers to forward that work (as he hath now done among us by thoſe worthies in <hi>PARLIAMENT</hi>) reſolve upon it, that the Dragon will wagge his Taile, and the times will bee very troublous.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:112503:12"/>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <note place="margin">When enemies are to goe downe</note>3. When enemies are to be defeated and deſtroyed: troublous times may then happen to Gods Churches, when either the diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing, or the deſtruction of wicked and malitious enemies is at hand; this wee finde that when <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Hoaſt were neareſt unto their ruine, then was the trouble of <hi>Iſrael</hi> greateſt; in the Churches ſtorms wicked men many times ſuffer ſhipwrack; their owne ſtirrings againſt, and ſtrivings with the Churches have beene the meanes of their owne ruine and trouble; <hi>Haman</hi> went downe in the time of the Churches trouble; and this is obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that the greateſt troublers of the State of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> have beene throwne downe in the times of the Churches trouble; had wee not had our troublous times, we had not ſeene ſo many <hi>Lucifers</hi> caſt downe among us! What times have more diſcovered enemies, what times have more croſſed enemies, nay what times have been more deſtructive to enemies then the times of the Churches trouble? theſe winds blow them no good, they alwayes preſage their downefall, if you look that great enemies ſhould fall downe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n expect troublous times for mine owne part I doe verily beleeve that all the troubles in <hi>Ireland</hi> and in <hi>England</hi> will end in the ſhame and confuſion of many powerfull and politicke enemies; ſuch who begin the Churches trouble muſt periſh ere the Church hath peace.</p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. <note place="margin">When mercies are at hand.</note> 
               <hi>When the Church is nigh to the enjoying of ſome great and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected mercy:</hi> this is obſervable, that the Churches greateſt mercies have ſprung out of the greateſt troubles; Shee hath not enjoyed ſuch mercies in her calme ſeaſons, as ſhee hath in her blu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring times, the nearer the woman is to the time of her delivery the quicker and the ſharper are her pangs and paines, when the froſt is neareſt to its breaking, then is the aire ſharpeſt in its pinch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; the Churches good is not divided from the Churches trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, under toſſings and tumblings ſhe is not onely expecting but prepared and fitted for mercies, the croſſe going of the wheeles doth further the right going of the Clocke, the fruitfulneſſe of the ſpring is it not hindred by the ſharpneſſe of the Winter; the Churches troubles are far from hindring the comming in of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, the Sun will ſhine though the winds blow, and the ſtronger the gale of wind is the quicker is the diſpatch of the ſhip unto the deſired haven; we ſee that when <hi>Pharaoh</hi> was in his greateſt rage,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:112503:12"/> then <hi>Iſrael</hi> was nigh unto deliverance; out of that troublous wombe came their greateſt quiet; if there were no warre there would bee no victory; though troubles create not mercies, yet they occaſion and antecede mercies, and it is Gods manner to give great mercies in troublous times, I am verily perſwaded that <hi>England</hi> which is now in great trouble is bigge with childe of ſome extraordinary mercy, wee may not thinke that theſe trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles ſhall end without a bleſſing, even that longed for reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion both of Church and Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>Let the conſideration of theſe things ſtay your thoughts and ſettle your mindes under the apprehenſion and ſenſe of theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent troubles.</p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> Thirdly, this may adviſe us well to prepare our ſelves for dayes and times of trouble; the counſell is ſeaſonable, for we have juſt feares ſtarted up among us of very troublous times to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall us.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>England</hi> hath at this day.</head>
               <note place="margin">Motives to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous times.</note>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>time troubling ſinnes;</hi> it is the ſinnes of a people that troubleth times; and brings downe diſquietneſſe; that which is the trouble of Heaven, and the trouble of the heart, will bee alſo the trouble of a Nation: I ſay that ſinnes of all ſorts, and in all ſorts ſo abounding amongſt us as they doe, cannot but bring with with them much and great trouble unto the whole Land: have wee not among us all Land waſting, and Land weakening ſins? moſt of <hi>our Paſtors</hi> are either ignorant and blind, or corrupt and unſound, or ſcandalous and wicked; ſo farre from reforming themſelves that they are enemies unto the much deſired Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, <hi>They ſee vaine and fooliſh things, and doe not diſcover unto</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lamen. 2. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>the people their iniquity to turne away their captivity;</hi> may not God ſay, <hi>Many Paſtors in</hi> England <hi>have deſtroyed my vineyard,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ierem. 12, 10. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>and troden my portion under feete, they have made my portion a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate Wilderneſſe, they have made it deſolate and being deſolate it mourneth unto me?</hi> Many of <hi>our Rulers and great ones,</hi> are Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous, Adulterous, full of pride, and idleneſſe, leading many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands into wickedneſſe by their evill example following the foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps, of <hi>Ieroboam</hi> who made <hi>Iſrael</hi> to ſinne; and as for <hi>the people</hi> of the Land, the pride of <hi>Moab,</hi> the cruelty of <hi>Edom,</hi> the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:112503:13"/> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the Apoſtaſie of <hi>Judah,</hi> together with the abundance of all ſins taketh hold of them; wee are an exceeding ſinfull people before the Lord and what can we expect ſhould bee the iſſue but troublous times?</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Troublous times warnings,</hi> God hath fired many Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, and ſhot of many warning pieces among us, which doe tell us that troubles are comming toward us, not onely <hi>Germany,</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> are all on a fire and flame, but we have the breakings out of the ſame among us by moſt unhappy diviſions between Prince and people; <hi>O for the diviſions of</hi> Reuben <hi>there ſhould bee great thoughts of heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>Time troubling enemies;</hi> we have lodging and lurking among us men of no Religion, (ſwarmes of Atheiſts) men of a falſe Religion (a great Popiſh party;) men of no rank and quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty whoſe mouths are full of ſcoffes and hands full of bloud, unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and baſe <hi>Cavaliers</hi> whoſe onely hopes lye in this that ſhortly they ſhall raviſh our virgins, defloure our wives, cut our throates, and divide our eſtates; what meaneth the countenancing and maintaining thoſe vermine and of-ſcouring of the Land, but that troublous times are at hand? certainly the kingdom cannot vomit out theſe frogs or quit it ſelfe of theſe Locuſts without much adoe.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>time troubling opinions:</hi> all hereſies are bitter ſprings and can produce nothing but troubles within a Church, when the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies of <hi>Arrius, Pelagius, Arminius, Socinus,</hi> and others crept into the Churches they did not a little encreaſe the troubles of the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterne and weſterne parts of the world, and for mine own part I cannot beleeve but that the like effects wil follow in this kingdom by mens deſerting of old truths and embracing of new errors; when people turne <hi>Anabaptists, Eatonists, Tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>kites, Antinomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Familiſts</hi> and what not; this will fill a Land with trouble and diviſion.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, <hi>time troubling actions;</hi> men ſtudy nothing more than how to be unquiet; each man is full of diſcontent, and ſet upon thwarting and croſſing, who almoſt among us is not for his owne will and way? and ſo that their egge may be roaſted, they care not though the kingdome burne for it.</p>
               <p>Finding theſe things among us wee have great cauſe to feare that God is going about to make our times troublous.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:112503:13"/>
               <p> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, It is to bee ſuſpected that our long enjoyment of peaceable times hath eaten up our expectation of, and preparation for troublous times: we dreame of a durable peace and <hi>put away the evill day from us,</hi> as did the <hi>Iewes;</hi> few perſons doe thinke of<note place="margin">Amos 6. 3.</note> troubles before hand and moſt wil not believe that they ſhall have troubles though they ſee nothing above them, but a cloud of bloud, and behold nothing beneath them but a red Sea.</p>
               <p> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, That troublous times are therefore to hard for many becauſe they are not well prepared and fitted for them, and indeed every the leaſt trouble will bee too ſtrong for an unarmed and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prepared Chriſtian: But happily you will ſay what would you have us to doe, that when troublous times come, we may look up and hold out?</p>
               <p>My advice is this.</p>
               <p> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, <hi>Keepe faire quarter with heaven;</hi> let not God bee your enemy or one that frownes upon you when troubles come; <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint</hi>
                  <note place="margin">10. Preparatives againſt troublous times. Iob 22. 21.</note> your ſelves <hi>With him, and be at peace, and thereby good ſhall come unto you:</hi> if men are in covenant with God and reconciled unto God in and through the Lord Jeſus they cannot bee und one by troublous times; the favour and love of God will bee ſecurity enough to Chriſtians in evill times, this was <hi>Noahs</hi> Arke that <hi>hee found grace in the eyes of God;</hi> hee had a friend in heaven.</p>
               <p> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, <hi>preſerve purity and peace within;</hi> let not Conſcience bee filthy or unquiet; the meeting of a foule Sea, and bluſtring ſtormes doe make the paſſage of the ſhip very troublous, and thus it is when a mans conſcience is filthy, and defiled by the love and power of luſts that there are ſeven abominations in it, if trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles come he cannot tell what to do with himſelfe, for now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is more unquiet then the times; beleeve me in this, that if troublous times, and a troubled conſcience do meete together, you will be of all men moſt miſerable: O therefore make it your worke, to get your Conſciences pacified, and purified through the ſprinkling of the bloud of <hi>Christ;</hi> labour that Conſcience may learne to read its own acquittall from the guilts of ſin, and that it may be very holy and ſpirituall, and then though you are caſt into the Seas and doe meete with the greateſt of dangers you are well provided for, if conſcience be not your hell, you are well enough for heaven.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:112503:14"/>
               <p> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, <hi>Affect not a life of eaſe and delicacy;</hi> could wee now me our ſelves to hardneſſe, wee ſhould the better endure troublous times: if wee ſhall daily pamper our bodies, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine under our wonted niceneſſe, being all for pleaſure and eaſe; if the meate that we are to eaſe is never ſine enough, if the wine and beare wee drinke can never be ſtrong or ſweete en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ough, if the beds whereon wee are to lie are not ſoft enough, and the clothes that we are to put on faſhionable enough to us: pray tell me, what ſhall we doe in troublous times? Good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians conſider, how will you be able to runne before a bloudy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier without ſtockings and ſhooes for tenne, twenty, or thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie miles together to ſave your lives, if you uſe now your feete to that niceneſſe, that you c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n ſcarce endure to tread upon a ſtone? how will you bee able to make the field your bed, or a ſtone your Pillow, if that you do not now uſe your ſelves to hard lodgings? I pity moſt of you who now put your heads in a bagge and muſt have hoodes for your faces, and what not for bravery and pleaſure, Alas! ſhould God bring many of you into the condition of your poore ſiſters in <hi>Ireland</hi> what would you doe? how could you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to be ſtript of your clothing, to hide your ſelves in dennes and caves, to drinke up puddle water, and to make acornes a feaſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you! ô that I could prevaile with you, now to inure your ſelves unto hardneſſe! it would put you into a fit temper for troublous times; it is noted of holy <hi>Bilney</hi> that being perſwaded he ſhould be burned for the Goſpell, he would often put his finger into the Candle to ſee if he could be able to endure the fire before he came into the fire; I wiſh that in <hi>England,</hi> this point were more preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and thought upon.</p>
               <p> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, <hi>Get quit of the Creature, in point of heart interest:</hi> this you ſhall finde, that thoſe waters which are running downe to the maine Ocean are more unquiet then waters that are nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed up in a well; and of this I am certaine that a worldly tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per is moſt unfit for a troublous time, if troubles ſhould come, then to have a Child in the heart, and an eſtate in the heart, will prove a greater trouble to a man then the trouble it ſelfe; O then get the Moone under your feete, and the world out of your hearts! Seeke not great things, and engage not your hearts to worldly things! trouble not the little world by the great world! be as
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:112503:14"/> was the holy Martyrs, who made nor Wife, nor Children, nor Eſtates a blocke to them in the way, and could <hi>cry out farewell world,</hi> and ſay, <hi>Bavaria is not ſo deare unto me as my Wife and c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ildren, yet for Chriſts ſake I will forſake them chearefully;</hi> when<note place="margin">Carpenter.</note> a man hath little or nothing to looſe he can the better endure the ſight of a thiefe, but when he hath great ſummes of money about him the comming of the thiefe is terrible to him; In this laſt yeares trouble at London, many had not beene ſo much troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led as they were, had they not beene ſo rich as they were; they then were as much taken up where they ſhould hide their wealth as in times paſt how they might get their wealth; hee was in a fit travailing poſture, that ſaid I have my learning in my head, and my ſtaffe in my hand, and as for the world take it who will. This I conceive, the world is for uſe, not for cumber: we are to hold it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our hands, and to keepe it from our hearts, if we meane well to paſſe through troublous times.</p>
               <p> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fifthly, <hi>take not Gods worke out of his hand:</hi> he that will med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of Gods part and not doe his owne duty ſhall never beare u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in troublous times, that, I intend is this, moſt people doe trouble themſelves about iſſues, and in meane time never keepe cloſe to duties; Oh! ſay ſome, Sir, for mine own part I could well paſſe over theſe troubles, but that which doth moſt trouble me is this, what ſhall become of my poore children when my throat is cut, or my life taken from me? who ſhall take care of them, and ſee that they be not brought up in the Popiſh and Idolatrous Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? ah poore creatures! doe not iſſues belong to God and duties to man? what, is that God on whom thou relieſt void of care and providence? Oh that we could make a deed of gift of all our Children to God, and that we could bequeath and commit them to God, truſting him withall, and over all leaving the ſucceſſe in his hands, who knoweth how to doe his owne worke better than man can direct him.</p>
               <p> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixthly, <hi>Make ſure your harberous and hiding places:</hi> Every ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly creature will provida it ſelfe of a place of refuge againſt the ſtorme commeth, and ſhould not Chriſtians fore ſeeing evill times get themſelves hiding places? Sure I am of this; that <hi>the name</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 18 10.</note> 
                  <hi>of the Lord is a ſtrong Tower, the Righteous runne into it and are ſafe,</hi> nay God calls upon his people thus: <hi>Come my people enter</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay 26 22.</note>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:112503:15"/> 
                  <hi>thou into thy Chambers and ſhut thy doores about thee: hids thy ſelfe as it were for a little moment until the indignation be overpast;</hi> theſe places do ſhew unto us that there are harbours to be had, ô that we could now bee ſecuring the preſence of God with us and the attributes of God for us, if God bee with us and for us wee are ſure to doe well enough; <hi>in the world you ſhall have trouble, but in me yee ſhall have peace:</hi> if we are once united to <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and are found in him then, we ſhall be ſafe, Chriſt will be ſanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and Tower of defence unto all that truſt in him.</p>
               <p> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Seventhly, Gather up hearts cordi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lls from the promiſes: when perſons are going to Sea they will furniſh themſelves with hot waters: and aske them the reaſon of the ſame they will tell you that the Sea is cold and unquiet, and the ſtomacke will be qualm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and now and then a little of this will doe them a great deale of good; the ſame ſay I of the ſpirits, which may bee gathered from Gods promiſes, when as men are going into troublous times this will beare up their ſpirits, and make them to beare their bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens with eaſe and joy; I ſay one dramme of covenant comfort will raiſe us up to admirable patience and delight; O that wee would skill our ſelves more and more in the promiſes, now is our time to find them out, and to get them into our hearts as well<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> as our heads if we have the promiſes to ſeeke when we are to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer we are undone.</p>
               <p> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Eighthly, furniſh your ſelves with ſpirituall armour; I finde that theſe troublous times have made men carefull to get armour into their houſes, but I doubt that if troubles ſhall boyle up to the height of malicious projects, many would be found naked and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>armed for their ſoules, its not a gilded ſword, or a dagger of yee that will ſtead a man in time of Warre, neither will a meere out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward profeſſion or ſhew of godlineſſe uphold the heart in evill times nay it muſt be grace in truth, and grace in power that will doe it. Wherefore above all things gaine.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Faith which may keep up your confidences upon the truth and goodneſſe of God in the promiſes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Patience which may enable you to ſtoope to the will of God in taking up the Croſſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The ſpirit of Prayer by which you may open your minde unto God, bring downe ſeaſonable ſuccours and aſſiſtances from
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:112503:15"/> GOD or bee able to commit your ſelves into the hands of God.</p>
               <p> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> Ninthly, well ſpend and improve your free times: if in dayes of peace men can get a ſtock of grace into their hearts, well husband all ſoule opportunities, be much in the exerciſes of humiliation and the practiſe of holineſſe, they will bee the better prepared for the worſt of times, <hi>the beſt doing Chriſtian will proove the right ſuffering Chriſtian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> Tenthly, <hi>Be ſitting of your ſelves for the best of ends,</hi> and then you are well prepared for the worſt of times; if men did think more frequently and ſeriouſly of death, and were daily putting themſelves into a dying poſture, they would be well prepared for troublous times, for he that is in caſe to die, will be in caſe to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer; here is our fault that we thinke of troubles, but we doe not thinke of death, or we looke upon troubles, as be falling us before death, whereas God knoweth many of us may be dead before the troubles come, as well as many of us die by the troubles when they come.</p>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>4</label> Fourthly, <hi>Learne to bee ſenſible of the times of</hi> Jacobs <hi>trouble:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe 4.</note> Let them have the ſame impreſſion upon our ſpirits which they had upon the ſpirit of the Prophet; he cries out, <hi>alas, for that day is great, &amp;c.</hi> ſo ſhould we, times of the Churches deſolation ſhould be ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es of the Chriſtians Lamentation; as the ſinnes ſo the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes of the Church ſhould worke us to much inward pity and compaſſion and to extraordinary and continued mourning and weeping.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Evils among men.</note> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> One Prophet ſaith, <hi>looke away from me, I will weepe bitterly, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>not to comfort me becauſe of the ſpoiling of the daughter of my people:</hi> and another Prophet ſaith, <hi>Let mine eyes runne downe with</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ierem. 14. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>teares night and day and let them not ceaſe for the Virgin daughter of my people is broken with a great breach;</hi> good <hi>Nehemiah</hi> ſits<note place="margin">Nehem. 1. 4.</note> him downe and weepes as if hee would have wept his heart out when he heard of the diſtreſſes and diſtractions of his brethren: This is the great ſinne of <hi>England</hi> that men looke upon the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of the times with a regardleſſe eye; <hi>Irelands</hi> miſeries, and <hi>ENGLANDS</hi> miſeries are not laid to heart; there are theſe evills under the Sunne, I wiſh that I could not charge them upon many.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:112503:16"/>1. One is to grieve at the Churches proſperitie: <hi>Ezra</hi> 4. <hi>Nehemiah</hi> 4.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A ſecond is to rejoyce in their miſery, as <hi>Pſalme</hi> 137. 3. <hi>Obad. ver.</hi> 12.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A third is to be given to mirth and paſtime when the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are in heavineſſe, as it is written; that the King and <hi>Haman</hi> ſate down to drink, but the City <hi>Shuſan</hi> was perplexed: <hi>Heſt.</hi> 3. 15. It is noted of the <hi>French</hi> that when the <hi>Gothes</hi> came in upon them, they were without ſenſe and feeling of their brethrens calamities, the Hiſtorian ſaith, <hi>Confundebatur vox morientium, &amp;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>alv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>anus de dei <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ubernati, lib. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>vox bacchantium, &amp; vix diſcerni poterat pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bis ejulatus qui fiebat in bello &amp; ſonus populi qui clamabat in circo, &amp;c</hi>) the voyce of the dying could hardly be diſtinguiſhed from the rorings of the drunken (then when the people who were without the City cried out for feare of the enemy, thoſe who were within the City made a noiſe at their ſports;) I doubt that wee have too too many like thoſe <hi>Gallants</hi> of old who would Crown their heads with ruſhes. when the Kingdom and Common-wealth was in great troubles; our feaſting, and dancing, and gaming doth witneſſe againſt us.</p>
               <p n="4">4. A fourth, <hi>Is not to mourne for the Churches miſeries,</hi> men have hard, and ſtony, dead and ſenceleſſe hearts, even like to the Prieſt and Levite, who paſſed by the wounded man, and had no compaſſion on him.</p>
               <p n="5">5. A fifth, <hi>Is to ſeeme to mourne and yet not to mourne for the troubles of the Churches;</hi> we have too too many funerall, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall mourners among us, men who are Clouds without waters; happily upon notice of the Churches troubles they can weepe, but they doe not mourne, alwayes teares from the eyes doe not argue mourning in the heart; <hi>Iſhmael</hi> could weepe as he went, and yet<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erem. 41 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> hee grieved not at the miſeries of <hi>Sion</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> and it is recorded that <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> did ſhed teares for <hi>Pompeys</hi> death which hee himſelfe cauſed: it is no new thing for to finde a teare in the eye, and joy in the heart; ſurely moſt of us are too ſudden, too ſhallow, too ſhort, and too open in our mourning which doth ſhew it to be wholly formall; beloved, let me intreat this of you: let no Church of God bleed, but do you bleed with them, weepe with them that weepe, weepe over <hi>Ireland, weepe</hi> over <hi>England,</hi> goe and ſay with the Prophet, <hi>I will waile and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:112503:16"/> howle, I will goe ſtript and naked, I will make a wailing like the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mich. 1. 8. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Dragons and mourning as the Owles: for her wound is incurable, for</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Meanes to bee mourners.</note> 
                  <hi>it is come into</hi> Judah, <hi>he is come unto the gate of my people even to Jeruſalem:</hi> and that you may do this, get a ſoft and tender heart, a heart that can truely mourne for your own ſins.</p>
               <p> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Get a publike ſpirit that can look abroad and make the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches<note place="margin">2.</note> cauſe and condition its owne.</p>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>5</label> Fifthly, <hi>This may worke upon us to take notice with thankeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the peacefull times which God hath continued unto us of this Land,</hi> when other Nations and kingdomes have had their tremb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and troublous times, we have (by free grace) enjoyd Halcion<note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns ſinne a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> peacefull time</note> dayes; had we layd under the miſeries of <hi>Germany, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> we would this day have prized our peace at an high rate; this is our great ſin.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That wee doe not take notice of our owne times of peace, and look upon the ſame as a great outward mercy which continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth many choice things unto us.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That wee doe not make a right uſe of our long enjoyed peace, we have abuſed our good dayes by running into all manner of riot and falling into ſeverall diviſions and contentions; <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> hath made her peacefull times her ſinfull times; the mildeſt Winters and Springs do not more bring forth the worſt and moſt of weeds, then our peaceable and quiet times hath occaſioned the committing of moſt foule and terrible ſinnes, wee have tainted our ſelves exceedingly, in ſo much that God might ſay of us, <hi>eaſe</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 1. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>ſlayeth the fooliſh; and the proſperity of fooles deſtroyeth them,</hi> it is a ſad thing to have peace, and to grow weary of it, or worſe by it, this will ſoone expoſe a Nation unto troublous times.</p>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>6</label> Sixthly, <hi>Let us take heed of haſtning our ſelves unto theſe troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous times:</hi> ô that wee could in <hi>Iacobs</hi> troubles ſee what may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall us; <hi>cui-vis poteſt accidere quod cuiquam poteſt,</hi> althings fall a like to all, and it hath never beene the happineſſe of any one particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar viſible Church long to ſtand in outward peace and beauty, I thinke God hath made this kingdome the miracle of the world for ſtanding peace, and may he not make it as miraculouſly miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable by times of trouble? and what if God ſhould do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſo? Oh the miſery of <hi>England,</hi> my heart bleeds to thinke of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of that day, as warres and troubles come in; all outward
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:112503:17"/> mercies and comforts would goe out; the withdrawing of the Sunne makes the night; the abſence of a good temper caſts the body i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>to weakneſſe, and if our peace bee gone, then <hi>the high wayes will bee un-occupied, the travellers will walke in by wayes;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 5. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Townes will not bee in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>abited, Cities will bee left deſolat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, and the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>es of Sion will lament, becauſe no man commeth to the ſolemns feaſts,</hi> now the Church will bee under a Cloud, ſcarcely viſible, and Religion will runne in ward, as the juice and ſap doth into the roote in times of winter; now Parents ſhall bee deprived of Children, Children of Parents; Husbands will be ſcattered from Wives, and Wives from Husbands, the enemy will ſacke, and ſpoile, rob and ſlay, raviſh and deſloure; nothing ſhall bee our owne but heavineſſe and diſtreſſe; with <hi>Germany</hi> we ſhall bee a field of bloud, and with <hi>Ireland</hi> a ſpectacle of miſery: Oh what mournings will bee in our ſtreetes, and what ſadneſſe in our hearts, what blackneſſe in our faces, and what deſolations in our kingdomes, you may thinke more than I can ſpeake, a ſad Trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die will beacted. Oh that we would feare theſe troublous times before wee feele them, and that now we would take that courſe which might prevent the falling downe of this bloudy cloud hanging over our heads; Brethren learne,</p>
               <p n="1">1. To get off the guilt of all thoſe Land troubling ſinnes which<note place="margin">Meanes to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent troublous times.</note> are among you, you muſt overthrow that which will overthrow all our mercies, and all our hopes, if the guilt of <hi>Englands</hi> Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, Cruelty, contempt of Ordinances, unfruitfulneſſe under the meanes of grace, Carnall ſecurity, embracing and entertaining errors againſt the foundation, formality in Religion, decaying in her firſt love, want of compaſſion to other bleeding Churches be not expiated in the bloud of Chriſt, <hi>England</hi> will bee an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done and miſerable Nation; <hi>What peace ſo long as the whoredomes</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Kings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>of they mother Iezabell and her witchcrafts are ſo many?</hi> O that we could tender up JESUS CHRIST unto God for <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> ſins.</p>
               <p n="2">2 To bee much in Nationall humiliation; the whole Land muſt bee mourned for, ô that wee could weepe over <hi>England,</hi> and grieve for the ſins of <hi>England;</hi> ſurely the whole Land muſt mourne and grieve, or it cannot long ſtand a Nation.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To deſire and further a Nationall reformation; there
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:112503:17"/> muſt bee a purging of the Church from its droſſe, there muſt be the ſetting up the power and purity of Ordinances, every man muſt ſtrive to reforme and amend elſe the Kingdome will ſoone fall aſunder.</p>
               <p n="4">4. To caſt out the endangering enemies of our Kingdome, if you ſhall ſuffer men of bloud and cruelty, enemies to God and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and not doe juſtice upon them, the kingdome cannot but be ruined.</p>
               <p n="5">5. To give off your daily courſe of ſinning, if God finde us a people ſet on our ſinnes, and that we will not give off the love and practiſe of iniquity hee will not ſpare us, how can wee expect the avo dance of troublous times, or the continuance of peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full times, when we fill up the times with iniquities.</p>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>7</label> Seventhly, and laſtly, <hi>Let us be farre from procuring troublous times unto the Churches of God,</hi> I know that it is a great ſin to bee an efficient malicious cauſe of trouble to the ſtate of GODS Church, the Apoſtle doth wiſh them cut off that were Church troublers, and <hi>Ioſuah</hi> proceeding to judgement againſt <hi>Ach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Galath. 5. 12.</note> ſaid, <hi>why hast thou troubled us? the Lord ſhall trouble thee this day Joſbuah</hi> 7. 25. it is no ſmall crime to be a troubler of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and here give me leave to acquaint you with the truth, for I finde that you are abuſed by the falſe ſuggeſtions of ſome who beare no good will to the <hi>Parliament</hi> or the welfare of Sion.</p>
               <p>There are ſome who are ſaid to bee the troublers of the State of the Church and Kingdome among us, who are no more guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of that charge then holy <hi>Elijah</hi> was, its not thoſe worthies now aſſembled in <hi>Parliament</hi> who ſeeke to their utmoſt to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve Gods Religion and all your liberties, and eſtates that have troubled the ſtate of our times, was it ever known that right Proteſtant Engliſh ſpirits did ever repute their choſen <hi>Knights, Burgeſſes, and Citizens,</hi> (who are the repairers of their brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and the reſtorers of pathes to dwell in) troublers of Church and State? Did you know but the fidelity and Loyalty of their hearts to the <hi>KING</hi> and kingdome, and behold their conſtant paines and diligence for the good of us and all our poſterity, you would bleſſe God for them, and account (as they doe indeed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve) worthily of them.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:112503:18"/>
               <p>There are others who are reall and actuall diſturbers and troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers<note place="margin">Who are ſo trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blers o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> our times.</note> of our times, namely, 1. <hi>Proud and diſcontented Prelates,</hi> together with their idle and ſcandalous followers, whoſe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits are ſwolne ſo bigge that they ſcorning reformation have throwne <hi>PETERS</hi> Keyes into <hi>Tibur,</hi> and have taken <hi>Pauls</hi> ſword in their hands, ſetting on that warre in the Land which may truly be called <hi>Bellum Epiſcopale: 2. Papiſts and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhly affected perſons,</hi> who having received the marke of the beaſt doe ſeeke to maintaine Idolatry among us, and for their idols re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to fight, <hi>tanquam pro aris &amp; focis;</hi> beleeve me that it is the ſmoake which commeth out of the Popes Kitching, thats ready to choake the Church, and doth make ſo many aking he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rts and weeping eyes among us, and our Warre is <hi>bellum papale. 3. Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and convicted perſons,</hi> who having formerly by unjuſt courſes, illegall patents, and other wayes of oppreſſion deceived us in our meates, drinkes, and apparell, doe now feare the ſentence and laſh of the I aw and ſeeke rather to imbroile the Subjects in war then to yeeld them a juſt ſatisfaction. 4. And in a word many en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted and upſtart Nobles with other <hi>beggarly and diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented Cavaliers;</hi> men without callings and Conſcience, even birds of prey who flutter up and downe, drinking healths to the Divell and their owne damnation, if they overthrow not the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and hang up the <hi>Round Heads</hi> by whom they meane the truely godly of the Land; theſe and the like are the malignant and moleſting party, into whoſe ſecret, let none of your ſoules come, with them have no confederacy, nay rather, diſcover their plots, reſiſt their perſons, and according to your Proteſtation joyne with thoſe (who are ready to live and die to doe you and yours good) to bring them to condigne puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>Thus when wee have done our utmoſt to prevent troublous times if God ſhall bring in troubles among us wee ſhall enjoy the peace of our Conſciences and may expect in his owne time the promiſed ſalvation and deliverance laid downe in the next part.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:112503:18"/>
            <head>Englands <hi>Salvations.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>But he ſhall be ſaved out of it.</head>
               <p>HEre wee have the light ſide of the Text, <hi>viz.</hi> the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of ſalvation out of their great trouble and miſery, times of deliverance ſhould follow times of trouble, we know that there is a threefold <hi>Salvation</hi> belonging to GODS Churches.</p>
               <p n="1">1. One ſpirituall which is the ſoules ſalvation from the power<note place="margin">A Threefold ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</note> of ſin in the ſanctification of their natures, when men are ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, then are they ſaved.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Another eternall which is the delivery of ſoule and body from hells damnation in the glorification of their perſons, when men are brought to heaven then are they ſaved.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A third is Temporall which is their freedome from out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward miſeries into which their ſins have caſt them; of this ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation our Text ſpeaketh. The ſenſe is this, that though they were for the preſent under many and great miſeries by their cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, yet a time was deſigned and decreed by heaven for their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance, they ſhould not alwayes bee bond-men in the hands of the <hi>Caldeans</hi> and <hi>Babilonians,</hi> there ſhould come the yeare of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilee,</hi> when the priſons ſhould be opened and the priſoners ſet free enjoying themſelves and their ordinances and their wonted peace and priviledges: whence I gather this point.</p>
               <q>That God hath his times and meanes wherein, and whereby hee<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Doct.</hi> 2. Gods Churches have ſalvation.</note> will ſave and deliver his Churches out of their great and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate troubles.</q>
               <p>Conſider, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> ſometimes God doth ſave his Churches and people from<note place="margin">From</note> troubles, they are exempted from deſtructions; <hi>Noah</hi> is ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved when the old world was drowned, and <hi>Lot</hi> was ſaved when <hi>Sodom</hi> was burned; there was 7000. ſaved from <hi>Iezabels</hi> fury;UNIT="In" and wee read of a remnant that eſcaped: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Sometimes God doth
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:112503:19"/> ſave his ſervants in <note place="margin">In</note> their troubles; though they are involved in the common miſeries of others, yet care is taken for them, that they ſhall be ſafe, <hi>Ieremiah</hi> was taken priſoner, and carried captive into <hi>Babylon</hi> yet God ſo orders the matter that not a haire falls from his head, hee was in more ſafety among the Heathens, then he could be among his owne people: Sometimes God doth ſave<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> his people out of their troubles; when he ſhall let them fall into great and ſore troubles, that their caſe ſeemes to bee deſperate, even ſuch as threatens death and ruine unto them, and out of which no poſſibility of deliverance by ordinary meanes doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare even now when they are as a Lamb or Sheepe in the mouth and paw of a Beare or Lion; ſhall ſalvation come in upon them, and a doore for deliverance ſhall be opened to them.</p>
               <p>2. You muſt know that God doth ſave his out of troublous<note place="margin">2 Sam.10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> times and conditions, ſometimes immediately by his owne migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie arme and power no creature being uſed, ſometimes medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately by the hand and help of thoſe creatures, whether Angels or men whom he is pleaſed to make choice of, not out of any neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity that he hath of them but to ſhew his Soveraignty over them and that readineſſe of diſpoſition that is in them to obey his will and helpe his Churches; wee reade of ſalvation by Angels, and of ſalvation by <hi>Joſuah</hi> and the Judges whom God raiſed up to bee both Typicall and temporall Saviours and deliverers unto his<note place="margin">Neh. 9. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> people.</p>
               <p>3. You muſt underſtand that ſalvation out of troubles being a temporall and outward mercy is vouchſafed to Churches in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and unto Chriſtians in particular upon Gods tearmes and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, that is. 1. <hi>If God ſee it to be good for them;</hi> there are certaine times when God though hee can by his power, yet hee will not in his wiſedome ſave and deliver his out of troubles, <hi>v. g.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1, <hi>When the truth is to be ſealed and ratified with the bloud of his</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Times when God will not ſave his out of miſery.</note> 
                  <hi>Saints;</hi> the Lord will ſometimes have his owne people to beare witneſſe unto the Goſpell by dying.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>When the Church is to be enlarged;</hi> the bloud of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs<note place="margin">ganguis martyrum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> is the ſeed of the Church, and when God will have it grow and encreaſe hee doth ſow and water it with the bloud of his Saints; the Church before and about the times of the tyrannicall
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:112503:19"/> Heathen Emperors when they ſlew tenne thouſands, and hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſands of her members did more increaſe them at other times.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>When enemies are preparing for, and haſtning unto their feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full deſtruction;</hi> God will give them time to ripen and fill up the meaſure of their ſinnes, to act out and over the wickedneſſe, and poyion that is in them, which they cannot doe if the Churches ſhould have their preſent deliverances.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>When Chriſtians are to bee manifeſted a ſacrifice of ſweete Savour unto God and the world;</hi> wee know that perfumes are ſweeteſt when they are throwne into the fire, and ſpices doe ſend out their ſmell when they are bruiſed in the morter, and Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans do ſend out the ſweet f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vour of their graces, then when they lie and die under their troubles.</p>
               <p>2. <hi>Then when God ſeeth it to be beſt for them:</hi> Gods time for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance and ſalvation is the beſt time, alwayes outward delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance is not beſt for Churches and Chriſtians; many times wee would have our mercies before that we are fitted for our mercies; all unſeaſonable deliverers would be hurtfull deliverances; GOD<note place="margin">Eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y 60. 22.</note> ſaith, <hi>I the Lord will haſten it in his time:</hi> our times are in Gods hands, and all our conditions for their kind and degree and time; he doth ſet downe when <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall goe into captivity, and how<note place="margin">Times when the Churches ſhall be ſaved.</note> long ſhe muſt remaine under it before ſhe be ſaved out of it; this I conceive that Gods times for his Churches deliverance out of troubles are theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>When miſery is come to its height,</hi> mans extremity is Gods opportunity, <hi>in the Mount will the Lord be ſeene:</hi> when things<note place="margin">Geneſis 22. 14.</note> to ſenſe are as bad as may be, ſo that there is little or no hope of amendment appearing, then ſhall deliverance come and ſalvation appeare, and that in a ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eciall and remarkeable way; when miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s do ſeeme to encloſe and encompaſſe Churches, that they are as a City beſieged round about, having all its paſſages ſtopt up, when miſeries doe preſſe and oppreſſe the Spirits to their miſery; yea when miſeries are lengthned out, and have boyled out them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to their utmoſt, then men can ſcarcely ſee how a Church or people can bee more miſerable, this is the time which God takes to ſave his Churches, as may appeare in the ſalvation of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the Red Sea, and of the <hi>Iewes</hi> in <hi>Hamans</hi> time.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:112503:20"/>2. <hi>When enemies are judgement ripe:</hi> God will let wicked men alone in their worke for a while, they ſhall have their day and yeare wherein they may fill up the meaſure of their wickedneſſe as did the <hi>Amonites;</hi> and this being done the Church ſhall have ſalvation according to that ſaying of God to <hi>Abraham, But in the fourth generation they ſhall come hither againe: for the iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Amorites is not yet full<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>:</hi> wicked men have much<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> wickednes to commit before the Churches come to be delivered.</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>When Churches are humbled under ſinnes and well prepared for deliverance:</hi> God, He never brings Churches out of miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled evills, till they are humbled for their ſinfull evi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ls; An unhum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled people are ſure to be an afflicted people; but when the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of a people is brought downe and layd low before God in all humilitie, when a people is thus fitted for deliverance it is at hand as we may ſee in <hi>Manaſſes</hi> and the <hi>Iſraelites.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 12, 13. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>When prayers are ſounding:</hi> uſually the Lord doth make the ſpirit of prayer the <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> to the work of deliverance; I meane hee makes men to bee much and mightie in prayer; he gives them enlarged hearts in prayer, they ſhall ſtrive and wra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle with him in prayer, and then ſalvation ſhall come in; we ſee that <hi>Daniel</hi> was much in praying when the Church was neare unto her deliverance, and the Chriſtians met in prayer the ſame night that <hi>Peter</hi> was delivered.</p>
               <p>3. <hi>In that way which ſe m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th good in his own eyes:</hi> God will go his own way in the ſaving of his, ſomtimes he will effect their ſalvation ordinarily in an uſuall and common way of providence; ſometimes he will give them ſilvation extraordinarily in a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail us and miraculous way of providence, even by weake means, no meanes and againſt meanes, as may appeare in <hi>Iſraels</hi> delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance out of <hi>Aegrpt,</hi> and at the Red Sea, and in the deliverance of the three Children out of the fiery furnace, and <hi>Daniel</hi> in the Lions denne together with many others.</p>
               <p>The truth of this propoſition will appeare unto us.</p>
               <p n="1">1. By the witneſſe of theſe Scriptures; <hi>Bleſſed art thou O Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, who is like to thee O people, ſaved by the Lord? The Lord is my</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut 33 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. Exod. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Pſalme 9<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, 12.</note> 
                  <hi>ſtreagth and ſong, and he is become my ſalvation: God is my King of old, working ſalvation in the midſt of the earth;</hi> when the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell had ſpoken unto <hi>Daniel</hi> of the greatneſſe of the miſeries of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:112503:20"/> the Church under Antiochus, he ſaith, <hi>and at that time thy people ſhall be delivered</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. By th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe confirming grounds.</p>
               <p>Firſt, In God there is every thing which may make for the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of his peo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le out of troublous times: As,</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Might and power,</hi> he is one able to ſave, <hi>Eſa. 63. 1. Our God whom we ſerve is able to deliver us from the burning fierie fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Daniel 3. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Yea ſo omnipotent is God that nothing is able to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand his power in ſaving his out of trouble, and therefore it is often ſaid that with a mighty and a ſtrong hand even as it were by force of Armes hee brought them out of the houſe of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Mercy and Love</hi> unto his Churches and people, God doth not ceaſe to love his when they are in Captivity and Calamity; his bowels are troubled for them and therefore he will ſurely have<note place="margin">Ierem 31. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> mercy upon them and deliver them; had God no love in him, not love unto his Churches, then they might lie and rot in the priſon, but we know that he loves them with an unchangeable love, they are his darlings, deare and tender unto him, and this makes him to ariſe to their deliverance; <hi>Iſrael is my ſonne even my firſt b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rne</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 4. 12. 13</note> 
                  <hi>let my ſonne goe</hi> ſaith <hi>Moſes</hi> to <hi>Pharaoh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Will and deſire,</hi> God is willing to ſave his people; <hi>Loe this</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay 15, 9. Daniel 3. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>is our God, we have waited for him and he will ſave us, and hee wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l deliver us out of thy hand O King:</hi> God hath a readineſſe of min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to ſuccour and ſave his children out of troubles, and what can hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their ſalvation?</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Wiſedome and skill, the Lord knoweth how to deliver the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Peter 2, 9.</note> 
                  <hi>out of temptations:</hi> all wayes and meanes for ſalvation are to be found in God.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Faithfulneſſe and truth:</hi> God hath undertaken to ſave, and promiſed deliverance; <hi>but upon Mount Zion ſhall be deliverance</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Obadiah v. 17. Zech. 8. 7, 8.</note> 
                  <hi>and there ſhall be holineſſe, and the houſe of</hi> Jacob <hi>ſhall poſſeſſe their poſſeſſions:</hi> and againe, <hi>thus ſaith the Lord of Hostes, behold I will ſave my people from the Eaſt Country, and from the West Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and I will bring them, and they ſhall dwell in the midſt of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, and they ſhall be my peopl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>; and I will be their God in truth and in righteouſneſſe,</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Care and provid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nce;</hi> as the generall care of God goeth
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:112503:21"/> along with all his Creatures, ſo his ſpeciall care and providence is held over his Churches and doth compaſſe them as the hills doe compaſſe <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> hence it was that <hi>Noah</hi> had his Arke and <hi>Moſes</hi> his basket or Cradle of Bulru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hes</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Name and Title,</hi> God is ſtiled in one place the <hi>Saviour of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ierem. 14. 8. Pſalme 40. 17. 1 Chro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. Pſalme 65. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in another place a <hi>deliverer;</hi> and in a third place <hi>the ſalvation of his people,</hi> now theſe Titles are made good in this Act of free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his people and taking them out of their miſerable conditions.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Soveraignty and dominion;</hi> God is Lord and King; the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler and over-ruler of all perſons and actions, men and devills, death and the grave, heaven and hell are at his diſpoſall: every condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 45 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> of peace and trouble, light and darkneſſe are his creatures: all things ſtoore to him, and are ruled by him; now having this abſolute command over all, he can with a nod, or a word make the Seas to give up their de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d and command deliverances for <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> the creature ſhall bee ſo farre from reſiſting and oppoſing his will that it ſhall further and haſten the ſame, and therefore it is that the Churches have their deliverance.</p>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> Secondly, <hi>In the Lord Ieſus,</hi> who is the great and mighty Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour and one that ſaveth his Churches ſpiritually and eternally; be having ſaved them from the greateſt danger by ſin will alſo ſet out himſelfe to ſave them out of the leſſe danger by miſery; he is one that goes along with <hi>Iacob</hi> in all his troubles; he it was that was<note place="margin">Daniell 3. 25.</note> in the burning furnace with the three Children; hee was in the Ship with the Diſciples upon the Seas, and he is that <hi>Michael, the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Daniell 12. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>great Prince which ſtandeth up, and ſtandeth for the Children of thy people:</hi> We may not conceive the Church to be under miſery and trouble, but <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> puts himſelfe into its condition: in their affliction he is afflicted; Chriſt is perſecuted when they are<note place="margin">Iſay 63. 9. Acts 9. 6. Hebrewes 4. 15.</note> perſecuted; hee is an High Prieſt touched with our infirmitie: and he will ariſe and ſhew himſelfe to bee on his Churches ſide, and doth never faile them in preſent aſſiſtance, and ſeaſonable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance; all the dangers of the Church are but the awakenings of Chriſt, and the calling of him forth unto their ſuccour, he will now be working for their good, he ſaith for the oppreſſion of my Church, I will ariſe; they ſhall not alwayes lie among the pots, be in the graves, and burne in the fire; I will not alwayes ſtand look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin">Pſalme 12.</note> upon their miſeries, but will come downe rebuking their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:112503:21"/> and delivering their perſons, for they are my fleſh and bone, even ſuch whom I tender as a man doth the apple of his eye.</p>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> Thirdly, <hi>In the enemies and troublers of the Church:</hi> I know that there is no will in them to further the Churches deliverance, they are their oppreſſors and would ſtill detaine them under bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage as wee may ſee in <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> yet there is a neceſſity in reſpect of them that the Churches be delivered, For</p>
               <p n="1">1. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ride of their heart muſt be taken downe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Their projects and purpoſes muſt be broken in pieces.</p>
               <p n="3">3 They muſt returne with ſhame and diſhonour.</p>
               <p n="4">4. They muſt have their ſpirits filled with vexation and indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.<note place="margin">Pſalme 112. 10. Prov. 11. 8.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. They muſt come into miſery themſelves: and in a word,</p>
               <p n="6">6. They muſt be made to confeſſe that great is the truth, and it<note place="margin">Zech. 12. 3.</note> will prevaile; ſtrong is Chriſt, and he will overcome; heavie and burthenſome is <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> even ſuch a ſtone, that all that burden themſelves therewith ſhall be cut in pieces.</p>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>4</label> Fourthly, <hi>In the Churches themſelves,</hi> to make this cleare to you, Note, 1. That the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>God</hi> is not made only for miſery, but miſery is made for the Church: miſerable conditions are the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per portion of wicked men: dangers are accidentall to Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and brought upon them for an end better and beyond troubles and therefore they muſt not alwayes lie under troubles.</p>
               <p>2. That the Churches of God under troubles and dangers are very praying; we ſee that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> under <hi>Pharaohs</hi> bondage cried to God and plyed him with prayers, now this very practiſe of theirs did not a little further their deliverance from <hi>Pharaoh; I ſought the Lord and he heard me: and delivered me from all my</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exo. 2 23, 24, 25 Pſalme 34. 4. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>feares:</hi> againe, <hi>this poore man cried, and the Lord heard him, and ſaved him out of all his troubles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>3. That Gods Churches and people muſt be revived, and reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and ſweetly refreſhed after their ſtormes and ſufferings; <hi>thou which haſt ſhewed me ſore and great troubles ſhalt quicken me againe, and ſhalt bring mee up again from the depths of the Earth:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſalme 7. 20.</note> Againe, <hi>I have ſeene his wayes, and will heale him, I will lead him</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay 57. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>alſo, and reſtore comforts unto him and his mourners:</hi> one more, <hi>I</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ierem. 30. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>will restore health unto thee, and I will heale thee of thy wounds ſaith the Lord, becauſe they called thee an out-caſt, ſaying this is</hi> Zion <hi>whom</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay 57. 16.</note>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:112503:22"/> 
                  <hi>no man ſeeketh after:</hi> how could this befall them if that they were not ſaved out of their miſeries? if they were ſtill held under, their ſpirit would faint and faile within them.</p>
               <p>4. That the Church of God muſt have the free and comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> uſe of Ordinances, when they were in a ſtrange Land they<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> could not ſing the Lords Song: the very ſacrifices of the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi> were the abomination of the <hi>Aegyptians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>5. That Songs of praiſes for deliverance muſt be found in the mouths of Gods people, according to that ſaying of <hi>David, Thou</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>art my hiding place, thou ſhalt preſerve me from trouble: thou ſhalt compaſſe me about with Songs of deliverance: Sclah.</hi> which could never bee unleſſe they received ſalvation from the Lord.</p>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> In the firſt place, we may take notice of the ſingular priviledge of the Church of God, that hath the priviledge of deliverance and ſalvation.</p>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>1</label> But you will ſay wicked men partake of deliverance out of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 1.</note> as well as the godly, and how then doe you make the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches deliverance ſuch a priviledge?</p>
               <p>I anſwer that wicked men are many times kept from, and<note place="margin">Sol. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> delivered out of dangers, but yet they have not the deliverance of the Church, For</p>
               <p n="1">1. They are delivered as creatures not as Children.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They are delivered by common providence, not by any ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall promiſe made to them, or applyed by them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Their deliverance is ſo farre from being a bleſſing that it is turned into a curſe unto them, it were farre better for them to lie in Chaines, and to die under miſery then to bee delivered, for by their deliverance they take an occaſion to be more free and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to commit ungodlineſſe; it is to them a very ſnare, and doth mightily enthrall them into the hands of Satan.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Their deliverance is not out of any love or reſpect which God doth beare unto their perſons, but under deliverances they are hated and abhorred of God.</p>
               <p n="5">5. They have onely an outward deliverance, for in the meane time they want all ſpirituall deliverance, and ſhall never enjoy an eternall deliverance; though they eſcape from <hi>Babylon</hi> they ſhall never eſcape hell, whereas the Church is delivered by the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, yea and all their temporall deliverances were but types unto
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:112503:22"/> them of their ſpirituall and eternall deliverances.</p>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>2</label> But you will ſay that the Church is not alwayes delivered, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a Church doth lie and die under miſeries.</p>
               <p>To this I anſwer.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Sometimes the Churches may have deliverance, and will<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sol.</hi> Hebrewes 11. 35</note> not accept thereof, it is written <hi>that they would not bee delivered becauſe they looked for a better reſurrection.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. That though the Church in its parts and members have not alwayes deliverance, yet in the whole it is ſaved and delivered; an Army may bee ſaid to eſcape though many Souldiers which made up the body thereof are ſlaine, wee may not imagine that when God maketh this promiſe of deliverance unto <hi>Iacob</hi> that none of the <hi>Iewes</hi> died or periſhed in their Captivity; <hi>Iacob</hi> in the general was ſaved out of it, though not every particular <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelite.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. That though God doth many times deny actuall deliverance from troubles unto his, yet he doth equall and exceed that delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in giving them delivery from ſinnes power, which is a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mercy then a thouſand outward deliverances or in giving them ſtrength and grace to endure death, and thereby tranſlating them unto heavenly glory; <hi>But Iſrael ſhall be ſaved in the Lord</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay 45. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>with an everlasting ſalvation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, That it is the ſafeſt and wiſeſt courſe to be with the Church of God, and to joyne and ſide therewith; God is now putting us to it, and we muſt ſhortly ſhew our ſelves to be of one ſide or other, wee cannot long bee neuters; what now is to bee dene, ſhal we deſert the Church and its cauſe out of ſlaviſh feares? if ſo, we are undone; for without the Church there is no ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Extra <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid in another caſe, <hi>except theſe abide in the Ship, yee cannot be ſaved:</hi> the ſame ſay I to you, if that you deſert and diſclaime the Church, yee cannot bee ſaved; deliverance goeth along with <hi>Iacob,</hi> the Churches ſide is the ſtrongeſt ſide, and the ſureſt ſide, becauſe its cauſe is the beſt cauſe; O my brethren what meane you to meditate a flight, and now to turne polititians, even a people ſo ſhie and ſubtill in your Religion, as if that your policy not your piety ſhould ſecure you? I conceive that Church leavers and Church forſakers are in the greateſt dangers, its not your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming from the Saints, that wil ſave either your eſtates or lives<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:112503:23"/> I have read a ſtory how that when the <hi>Papists</hi> in <hi>England</hi> were complotting with the <hi>Spaniard</hi> abroad to bring in their <hi>cried up Armado;</hi> the time drawing nigh for their comming over, the Engliſh Catholikes ſent over to the grand contrivers of that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne to know what courſe they had taken for their ſafety, unto whom this anſwer was made, we know you to be Catholike, but we feare your goods wil be <hi>Lutherans:</hi> no further ſecurity can we<note place="margin">Vos catholici, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> vestra Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therani.</note> undertake for; it is no ſecurity to men either to be of no Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; or to be of a falſe religion; if you will be ſafe be of the true reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, be with ſuch who have the promiſe with them; I know that every man wiſheth his own and his families ſafety in theſe times, now our ſafety is by cleaving to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> not by joyning with the Cavaliers; the former are men of piety, fidelity, gravitie goodneſſe, and loyalty: the latter a baſe, ſwearing, whoring, ſtealing, and murderous company, who ſtinke in all places where they come, being the abominations and burdens of all the <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne</hi> parts; can you imagine that the ſafety of you and your po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterities is bound up any where then within the walls of the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament?</hi> Looſe this <hi>Parliament,</hi> and all is loſt, Religion is loſt, Liberty loſt, eſtates loſt yea and the glory of <hi>England</hi> loſt.</p>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> Thirdly, Let us expect and waite for the deliverance of <hi>Iacob,</hi>in a praying and believing way, what though the Churches mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries are great grievous, and of long continuance yet bee not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected; neither doe you deſpaire your hearts: Remember what is written; <hi>O my people, ye ſhall know that I am the Lord, when I</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezek. 37 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>have brought you out of your graves: ſtand ſtill, fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re not, behold</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exodus. 14. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>the ſalvation of the Lord which he ſhall ſhew unto you this d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y:</hi> when were theſe words uttered? was it not then when they were go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the Red Sea? Brethren pluck up your ſpirits: deliverance ſhall come to the Church; God will make a way for our eſcape: Oh that we could now ſet our prayer and faith on working; our times are fitted for prayer and faith: had we not theſe two pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars for our u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>holding, I know not what we ſhould doe: come therefore into the preſence of God ſeeking the Churches ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and deliverance, ſay with <hi>David redeem: Iſrael O God out of all</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſalme 25. 22. 13. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>1. Eſay 62. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>his trouble, remember</hi> David <hi>and all his troubles.</hi> Oh that with the Prophet we could ſay, <hi>For Zions ſake will I not hold my peace, and for Jeruſalems ſake I will not reſt, untill the righteouſneſſe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:112503:23"/> thereof goe forth as brightneſſe, and the ſalvation thereof as the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſalme 53. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>lamp that burneth:</hi> Let this be the daily wiſh of our ſoules, <hi>Oh that the ſalvation of Iſrael were come out of Zion:</hi> further be you intreated to exalt your faith in believing that the Church ſhal have deliverance, that the earth ſhal open and bring forth ſalvation; and<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſay 45. 8. Eſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 26. 1.</note> that <hi>God will appoint ſalvation for walls and bulwarkes,</hi> what though the times doe threaten ruine and deſtruction, yet know,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That God is above all the troubles of his Churches, and doth command them: ſo that they ſhall never exceed his will and power, though dangers are great yet God is greater then all dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That God hath all deliverances in his hand, and can <hi>command</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſalme 44. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>deliverances for Iacob,</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> ſaith, <hi>I forme the light, and create</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſay 45. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>darkeneſſe, I make peace and create evill: I the Lord doe all theſe things:</hi>
               </p>
               <p> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Say not in the feare of your hearts, <hi>by whom ſhall Iacob ariſe?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Amos 7. 5. Eſay 33. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>for he is ſmall.</hi> Looke upon God who is, <hi>our arm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> every morning, our ſalvation alſo in the time of trouble:</hi> doe not reaſon unbelee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vingly, can theſe dry bones live or Churches under ſuch deep dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers be delivered? I aſſure you brethren; that dry bones ſhall live, and miſerable Churches ſhall bee delivered; Say not that you ſee no meanes for deliverance? all meanes are ſhut up in God, and he hath means beyond our ſight: what men either cannot, or will<note place="margin">Eſay 63. 4.</note> not doe that God can and will doe; marke what God ſaith, <hi>the yeare of my redeemed is come: and I looked, and there was none to helpe: and I wondred that there was none to uphold, therefore mine owne arme brought ſalvation to me:</hi> doe not ſtand objecting the many blockes that ſtand in the way, or the many improbabilities and impoſſibilities for deliverance! but know that God maketh his way through the Seas, he is omnipotent; a wonder working <hi>God</hi> to whom nothing is impoſſible, remember what is written <hi>who art thou O great mountaine before Zurabbabel, thou ſhalt become a</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Zech. 4. 7</note> 
                  <hi>plaine, and he ſhalt bring forth the head ſtone thereof with ſhoutings crying grace, grace unto it:</hi> be not a diſheartned people under the <hi>Churches</hi> trouble, but lift up your eyes to the hils whence ſalvation commeth; ſay with <hi>Dan, I have waited for thy ſalvation ó Lord:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Geneſis 49. 18. Pſalme 3. 8. Eſay 49. 8. Pſalme 69. 35.</note> 
                  <hi>Salvation belongeth unto the Lord,</hi> and he will helpe or raiſe up his Churches in a day of ſalvation; God will ſave <hi>Zion</hi> and build the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:112503:24"/> Cities of <hi>Iudah</hi> that they may dwell there and have it impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion.</p>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>4</label> Fourthly, Let us further the Churches ſalvation and deliverance; God doth many times ſave his Churches by meanes, he raiſeth up men Saviours, and men deliverers, and there is not a Chriſtian man and woman among us, but they may doe ſomething for tho Churches ſafety, though we cannot doe alike, yet ſomething we may do; will our riches and eſtates deliver bleeding Churches? part from that, you honour God with your riches when you lay them out for the Churches ſecurity, will your perſons further the ſalvation of <hi>Iacob?</hi> goe out in your might and helpe the Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the mighty; have you no Silver or Plate, or bodies that are ſerviceable, then helpe the Church with your prayers, and tears go to God and mind him of his promiſe, put him to it, give him no reſt night nor day till hee eſtabliſh and till hee make <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> a praiſe in the earth; ô let none us be<note place="margin">Eſay 62. 6, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Neuters, let none of us ſit ſtill; let us up and be doing, and no doubt but God will be with us, and for his Churches.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:112503:24"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:112503:25"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:112503:25"/>
            <head>ENGLANDS HOPES.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>HOSEA 2. 15.</bibl>
               <q>And the Valley of Achor for a doore of Hope.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this Chapter we have a double repreſentation of Iſrael, and a double repreſentation of God:</p>
            <p>Firſt, Iſrael is repreſented unto us, under,</p>
            <p>1. A ſinfull condition; She was idolatrous, adulterous, unmindfull of, and unthankfull for mercies: She ſinned under, againſt, and with mercies, we reade of her whoredomes, adulteries between her breaſts, play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the harlot, going after lovers, not knowing that God gave her corne, and wine and oyle, multiplying her ſilver and gold which ſhe prepared for <hi>Baal,</hi> ſhe had her dayes of <hi>Baalim,</hi> and times for lewdneſſe.</p>
            <p>2. A ſorrowfull condition; Shee was divorced, ſtript na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, made as a wilderneſſe, ſet as a dry land, ſlaine with thirſt, deprived of mercies, hedged in with thornes, and made every way miſerable.</p>
            <p>Secondly, God is repreſented unto us, under,</p>
            <p>1. Acts of ſevere juſtice: He doth quickly eſpie, ſharply rebuke, terribly threaten, and miſerably puniſh Iſrael for her
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:112503:26"/> ſins, ſhe is left to enjoy the recompences of her lewdneſſe, and made to feele the fury of an angry God.</p>
            <p>2. Acts of ſweeteſt mercy: In the midſt of wrath God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members mercy, under her afflictions he makes her promiſes, notwithſtanding her ſins which ſhe had committed, and her miſeries which were to be endured, God doth tell her that hee will ſpeake to her heart words of comfort and pardon; and whereas for her ſins ſhe was juſtly ſtript of all outward and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward comforts, yet he would in his own time, and by his own free grace; make a full reſtitution of all good things unto her, it was not the miſery of her condition which ſhould hinder, or keep out the comming in of his mercy; <hi>From thence I will give her her Vineyard:</hi> even from the wilderneſſe: and whereas her heart under her miſeries might gather feares, and doubts, that God had quite forſaken and forgotten her, and that the tyde ſhould never turne: the Lord in the words read, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes to give her upholdings of ſpirit, ſaying, <hi>And the Valley of Achor for a doore of hope: q. d.</hi> Though my people by their ſins have forfeited all my mercies, yet my mercy ſhall give them mercies, and whereas their miſeries may make them fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and deſpairing. I will give to them ſuch matter and ground of confidence, that they ſhall have ſtrong hopes in me, and of my mercy and love unto them.</p>
            <p>The words you ſee are a branch of the promiſed mercy of God unto his ſinfull and afflicted people, wherein we may take notice of two things:</p>
            <p n="1">1. The thing, or the mercy that God undertakes to give them, and that is a doore of hope.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſigne, or token, or the meanes which God takes up for the aſſurance of this mercy unto them, and that is the valley of <hi>Achor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the firſt part, in briefe I ſhall ſay thus much; That in the<note place="margin">4. Sorts of doores.</note> Scriptures I reade of ſeverall doores, as 1. of Speech and ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terance, which is an open &amp; free mouth to preach the Goſpell; <hi>Praying alſo for us, that God would open to us a doore of utterance</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 4. 3.</note> 
               <hi>to ſpeake the myſtery of Chriſt:</hi> 2. Another of faith, which is the doctrine of the Goſpell, opening Chriſt to men, and entring men into Chriſt: <hi>God hath opened the doore of faith unto the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 14. 27.</note>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:112503:26"/> 3. A third of opportunity and liberty, which is a time and ſeaſon put into a mans hand for the edifying of others; and thus <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>A great doore, and effectuall is opened unto mee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 16. 9.</note> and againe <hi>When I came to Troas to preach Chriſts Goſpell, and</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 2. 12.</note> 
               <hi>a door was opened to me of the Lord.</hi> 4. A fourth of hope, which is the opening of a way for the raiſing up of the heart to an expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation<note place="margin">The doore of hope, What?</note> of mercy and reliefe, notwithſtanding the contrary de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert of ſin, and the preſent ſenſe of troubles, when the ſoule is made to know, that though its condition and ſtate for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent is very miſerable, yet it is not only within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe and poſſibility of mercy and reliefe, but ſhall in Gods time be admitted to the throne of Grace, and Cities of refuge, yea, and it can look out, and looke up to God in a waiting way for mercy, this is the maine nature of the doore of hope.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond part, we may take notice of 2. things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. What is this valley of <hi>Achor?</hi> this <hi>Achor</hi> was the firſt place of ground into which the Iſraelites came, being gotten over Jordan, as they went to take poſſeſſion of Canaan, we may reade where it did lie, <hi>Joſ.</hi> 15. 7. It was that valley wherein <hi>Achan</hi> (that troubler of Iſrael) was ſtoned, as you may reade, <hi>Joſ.</hi> 7. 24 and verſe 27. the word properly ſignifies, a <hi>valley of conſternation,</hi> or <hi>trouble;</hi> and here is one thing notable in this<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Achor,</hi> what it ſignifies.</note> expreſſion, it is not ſaid that I will give them a doore of hope in the valley of <hi>Achor,</hi> (that had been a wonderfull mercy) but I will give them the valley of <hi>Achor</hi> for a doore of hope: a ſpeech fit for God to utter, and which God only can make good.</p>
            <p n="2">2. How this valley of <hi>Achor</hi> became a doore of hope? which<note place="margin">The valley of <hi>Achor</hi> a doore of hope in 5. Reſpects.</note> I conceive thus:</p>
            <p n="1">1. As it was <hi>the firſt place on which they did ſet foot at the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into the hoped for Land,</hi> when God brought them into this valley, then their hopes began to be raiſed up, that ſurely they ſhould paſſe through the length and bredth of the Land of Canaan, God having brought them hitherto, he would alſo bring them further; the beginnings of mercies are pawnes of further, and greater mercies.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As it was a <hi>place of reſt and pleaſure</hi> unto them after their
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:112503:27"/> troubleſome paſſage through the Wilderneſſe, and their trembling paſſage over Jordan, this Valley was fruitfull and pleaſant, as we may reade in the Prophet, <hi>Sharon ſhall be a fold of flocks, and the valley of Achor a place for the heards to lie downe</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 65. 10.</note> 
               <hi>in, for my people that have ſought me:</hi> if God bring his people to pleaſant and fruitfull conditions, this muſt needs make them to pluck up their ſpirits, and fill them with hopes through believing.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As it was <hi>a place of divine pacification:</hi> in this valley, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<note place="margin">Joſh. 7. 27.</note> that act of <hi>Ioſhuahs,</hi> and the peoples, in ſtoning of <hi>Achan,</hi> God is ſaid to turn from the fierceneſſe of his anger manifeſted towards <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and at ſuch time when God ceaſeth to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with his people, the heart cannot but gather hope.</p>
            <p n="4">4. As it was <hi>the place wherein all the overthrowes of the Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites by any of the Kings which came out to fight with them ceaſed,</hi> for after they went out of this valley, they conquered in all the battels which they fought.</p>
            <p n="5">5. As it was <hi>the place of divine encouragement unto Ioſhuah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joſh. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 2.</note> here it was that the <hi>Lordſaid to Joſhuah, feare not, neither bee diſmaid, take all the people of Warre with thee, ariſe and goe up, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Out of the whole I ſhall raiſe up this concluſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That God doth give unto his Churches and people a doore of</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Doctr.</hi> The Church under its trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles hath a doore of hope.</note> 
               <hi>hope in their moſt miſerable and diſtracted conditions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As there is one doore which enters them into their ſorrows, and miſeries, ſo there ſhall be another doore which ſhall raiſe up their ſoules to an expectation of good and comforts. God doth ſo order the matter with his, that however their preſſures are heavy, and diſtractions many, yet divine help and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort ſhall appeare in a bending and bowing way towards them, notwithſtanding all that they ſhall ſuffer and endure, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne of good and comfort ſhall be both probable and poſſible unto them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That it is one thing to feare more evill under the feelings (of ſome evill, this doore of feare is the portion of the wicked) and another thing to hope for good, when men doe feele mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable evils.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:112503:27"/>
            <p>To look upon evill, is enough for feare, there muſt be good, elſe there can be no hope.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That it is one thing to apprehend divine grace and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to be, and that we are ſuch who greatly need it, and another thing to conceive a poſſibility of the ſame to a mans ſelfe: many may look upon mercy and help, in an abſolute and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple way, but few looke upon the ſame in a relative and reflect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing way: it is not enough to hope, to ſee the thing that is good and relieving, but it muſt withall ſee it as the thing which they muſt ſhare in.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the doore of hope is not made by any creature, it is God that doth create and beſtow it: And fourthly, to one man this doore ſtands more open, and is larger, unto another man it is ſtraiter and narrower: ſome there are who have much adoe, and doe ſtir mightily to bring themſelves under the hopes of pardoning and ſuccouring mercies, ſo great is their comming in, and on of their feares, that they are ready to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire, ſaying with doubting <hi>David, One day I ſhall fall by the hands of Soul,</hi> it may be many dayes and yeares are ſpent in trouble and heavineſſe before they can receive any hopes of their acceptance and deliverance, others there are, who can more eaſily looke up, and quickly eſpie the bendings and bowings down of mercy and reliefe to themſelves, they can conſidently without ſcruples and doubts conclude the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of promiſed mercy to themſelves: O the large hopes that are begotten in many Chriſtians who do lye under much miſery.</p>
            <p>Now that they have this doore of hope in troublous times, we might cleare in <hi>Abraham;</hi> had he not the doore of hope, when he ſaid to <hi>Iſaac, My ſon, God will provide? Moſes</hi> had a<note place="margin">Gen. 22. 8. Exod. 14. 13.</note> doore of hope when he ſpake to Iſrael, <hi>Stand ſtill, feare not, ſee the ſalvation of the Lord which he will ſhew you to day:</hi> This doore of hope was given to <hi>Paul</hi> when he was in great danger upon the Seas, In the ſeven and twentieth Chapter of the <hi>Acts</hi> verſes, 22, 23, 24, 25. The Jewes had this doore of hope, for <hi>Shechaniah</hi> tels them, that <hi>there was hope in Iſrael concerning</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezra 10. 3.</note> 
               <hi>this thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it cannot be otherwiſe, for,</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:112503:28"/>
            <p>Firſt, Gods name is <hi>the hope of Iſrael,</hi> as well as <hi>the Saviour</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reaſ. 1.</note> 
               <hi>thereof in time of trouble.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 4. 8.</note>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> Secondly, Chriſtians are ſtiled the priſoners of hope; <hi>turne your ſelves to your ſtrong holds, ye priſoners of hope.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 9. 12.</note>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, the nature of God is gracious, tender, and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, he is alwayes ſitting upon the throne of grace, and is very full of bowels and openings of divine grace towards ſuch as are his, and this makes him to hold out the planke, and to cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate a doore of hope: all a Chriſtians ſoule-refuges and hopes are grounded in the gracious nature of God.</p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>4</label> Fourthly, the nature of miſeries and afflictions in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are ſinking and deſpairing to humane ſpirits; if God ſhould leave man to the power of a miſerable condition, it would ſinke and drown him. I ſay that of an afflicted conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which we uſually ſay of fire and water, they have no mercy; here that is true which <hi>Strabo</hi> reports of the river <hi>Silias,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in all things ſink to the bottome, and nothing floats: the heart of man, if it were left without hope in times of miſery, would be as a naile caſt into the water, or much after the manner of one who is caſt into the deepes, that cannot ſwim: his ſpirit would faile; we have a proverbe to this purpoſe, were it not<note place="margin">Eſa. 57. 16.</note> for hope the heart would breake.</p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>5</label> Fifthly, the intention of God in afflicting, and puniſhing his, is very good: God doth not caſt down his children to caſt them off, he intends not their ruine, but their profit when hee doth chaſtiſe them, if he puts his into the furnace, he doth it to melt them, in that very way that the Goldſmith doth melt his Gold, only to purge out the droſſe, and to fit and frame them to be veſſels of uſe and honour to himſelfe, if he put the bridle on them, and ride them over hedges and ditches, and plowed grounds, and heavy wayes, it is but to bring down their ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born ſpirits, and to bring them to an obedient pace: Surely by all afflictions he doth but fit them for mercy; and doth not this yeeld the reaſon of their having now at ſuch times as theſe a doore of hope.</p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>6</label> Sixthly and laſtly, the people of God muſt act over-duties, and put themſelves upon meanes of pacification and attone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, under their greateſt miſeries: Now it is hope of good
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:112503:28"/> which is the loadſtone of all endeavours, deſpaire cuts off the uſe of all meanes, and makes men to quit all duty, if there ſhould appeare no way open for eſcape, if there were no back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doore to get out at, to what purpoſe ſhould men pray, and faſt, and beleeve, and humble themſelves, and ſtick to God for help and ſuccour: My Brethren, God will have his people to be in no condition wherein they ſhall not be dutifull and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to him, or neglect to uſe thoſe meanes whereby they may doe themſelves good.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This truth,</hi>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> Firſt, may diſcover unto us the different eſtate of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and the godly in ſuffering and ſorrowing times; For wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men they may have,</p>
            <p n="1">1. A doore of <hi>preſumption;</hi> they may build upon delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance<note place="margin">The ungodly mans doores in ſinfull and ſorrow full times.</note> and comfort, without ground and reaſon; I know none more ready to promiſe themſelves good, then men who have no title to the promiſes; the world is filled with a dead, and dark, and dreaming hope: Some of the Philoſophers cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led hope the dreames of waking men, and I may truly ſay, that moſt mens hopes are but dreames; as he ſaid of lovers, <hi>Sibi ſomnia fingunt,</hi> they fancy every thing ſhall be, becauſe they would have it ſo: ſo may I ſay, when I looke upon the ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſhneſſe, and carnall walking of moſt men in times of danger and trouble, and heare them ſay, that they hope for mercy and ſuccour from God: Truly theſe men doe build more upon imagination then reality; alas poore creatures, your dreames may cheare you whileſt you are aſleep, but they will terrifie you when you awake: O miſerable creatures, when you have hoped your hopes, it ſhall be with you, as it was with <hi>Ixius,</hi> who hoped for <hi>Juno,</hi> but inſtead of her he had a cloud that did all to bewet him, or as it was with the Heathen, who offered Sacrifice to <hi>Hercules</hi> to drive away their Wolves, and he tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented them more then their Wolves; my meaning is, you may look long enough, but no good ſhall come to you.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A doore of <hi>deſperation;</hi> in the ſenſe and apprehenſion of judgements and calamities they may, 1. Make a determinate judgement upon the impoſſibility of any good and mercy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to them, they cannot conceive that ſafety and delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:112503:29"/> ſhould come, nay they make it a thing impoſſible to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to the Haven and rock. 2. Miſerably ſink down in their ſpirits: oh, there is no hope, my puniſhment is greater then can be borne, ſo heartleſſe are they, that they ſuffer ſhipwrack preſently, and ſuffer themſelves to ſinke lower in their ſpirits, then they are in their troubles: O faithleſſe and hopeleſſe creatures, why do you give off your God, and fall down into the deepes? it is juſt with God to deny thoſe a doore of hope in times of miſery, who doe ſlight him in times of proſperity.</p>
            <p>But how is it with the godly? How? they have a doore of hope ſtanding before them: ſuch can ſay, I expect and looke for good from God, notwithſtanding all the evills I feele and ſuffer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> Object.</hi> But happily you will object and ſay, Sir, have god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men alwaies a doore of hope in diſtreſſed times? Remember whoſe ſpeech was that, <hi>My hope and ſtrength is periſhed from the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam. 3. 18.</note> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> and againe, <hi>Our bones are dryed, and our hope is loſt, wee</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 37. 11.</note> 
               <hi>are cut off from our parts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Sol.</hi> I have conſidered of theſe Scriptures which ſpeak out the Saints infirmities, they do not ſay that they had no doore of hope, but they ſhew the weakneſſe of their faith to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the ſame: the Well of water was nigh to <hi>Hagar,</hi> yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till her eyes were opened ſhe could not ſee it: the queſtion is not how clearly Chriſtians doe ſee the doore of hope, or how ſtrongly they are able to raiſe up their expectations, but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they have not a ground for to hope for good in evill times: wicked men can neither actually nor habitually hope, for they have no ground: the godly have a conſtant ground and cauſe for hoping, and when they cannot actually, yet they can habitually hope.</p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, this may raiſe up our hearts this day unto much<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe 2.</note> comfort and confidence: it is true that we have a doore of great miſery ſtanding very open before us, there is a threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and a trembling doore ſetting up in the Land, it may bee ſuch a door which may enter us into a bloody and civill War, the very beholding whereof may ſtrike us with ſadneſſe: Let me now tell you for your comfort:</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">Grounds of comfort.</note> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 1. That there neither is, or ſhall be ſet up within this Land
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:112503:29"/> any doore which ſhall enter us into miſery, but ſuch as the good Lord whom we love, and feare, and ſerve ſhall permit and ſuffer; God muſt ſuffer all our ſufferings, it is not all the power, plots, and projects of our revolted Nobles, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant party that can ſet up a doore of miſery at their pleaſure, God who hath the hearts, and the preparations thereof in his owne hands, hath the hands of them all in his hands, even to check, controll, and turne them at his own will.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That if ever God ſuffer men to ſet up a foredoore of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, he will beſtow upon his a backdoore of hope; God is as able as willing to ſet up doores of hope for his.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">Doores of hope.</note> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> 3. That God hath given to us this day many doores of hope, I ſhall name theſe unto you.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The doore of the promiſes</note> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. <hi>The full and precious promiſes of mercy and ſuccour;</hi> abundant is God in his undertakings to relieve diſtreſſed Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians? And what are all thoſe engagements of God for good unto his, but the letting fall of ſome hints of mercy before the ſoule to raiſe up hope; had we no promiſes, we could have no doore of hope, <hi>Remember</hi> (ſaith <hi>David) thy word unto thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 49.</note> 
               <hi>upon which thou haſt cauſed me to hope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But we have no particular promiſe of deliverance, and therefore how can wee make the promiſes a doore of hope?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> It is the promiſes of God in generall that are the doore of hope, ſo that if we can finde our particular condition in them, we may expect mercy and deliverance.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The doore of experiences.</note> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. <hi>Experiences of former times;</hi> this was <hi>Davids,</hi> and <hi>Pauls</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 17. 36. 37. 2 Cor. 1. 10.</note> doore of hope, and we ſhould make it our doore of hope; what God hath done at one time, he can alſo doe at another time; nay, he puts out himſelfe at one time, that future Ages may make him their hope at all times: Could we looke into dayes of old, and recall the yeares of the right hand of the moſt high, and ſee what God hath done for miſerable Churches, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed Chriſtians before us, nay, could we but live upon our owne particular experiences of the many paſſages of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, I thinke we ſhould have as wide a doore of hope as ever any people had.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The doore of prayer.</note> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. <hi>Enlargement of ſpirit:</hi> God hath poured out the ſpirit of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:112503:30"/> prayer upon the people of the Land, ſome, nay, many thouſands there are who come to the Throne of Grace, and doe mightily and daily wraſtle with God for a bleſſing upon England; and this is a ſtrong doore of hope<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it is that which keepes heaven doores open: we uſually ſay, that when the Cock begins to crow thick, then the day is neareſt breaking, and this is my hope, that England ſhall not miſcarry, becauſe ſhe hath ſuch a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aying people in it, goe into all the corners of the I and, and you ſhall finde many <hi>Jacobs,</hi> many <hi>Daniels,</hi> and many <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miahs,</hi> who doe exerciſe themſelves in praying, ſurely a childe of ſo many prayers cannot periſh.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doore.</note> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. Frequency of humiliations: God hath ſet up in England by authority, twelve ſolemne humbling dayes in a yeare, which is ſuch a mercy, that England never enjoyed, and theſe dayes are in many places ſolemnly kept; in theſe dayes multitudes meete together, even whole Armies of Chriſtians beſet God, the conſiderable part of the Land doe weep and mourne, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling themſelves for their ſins before the Lord, and ſeeking mercy and pardon for the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The doore of utterance.</note> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> The erection of further and greater meanes of light and knowledge: the doore is ſet open for painfull and conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous preachers in ſuch pariſhes and places in the Kingdome that for many yeares paſt never enioyed the ſoule-ſaving Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, the ſpirituall food in many places is doubled and tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, an excellent evidence of much good to this poore Iſland.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The doore of ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ation.</note> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 6. The acceptation of ſacrifices and ſervices: God hath had reſpect to the prayers and humblings of his people, there hath ſcarce been a day of ſolemn meeting, which God hath not crowned with ſome ſeaſonable and anſwerable returne; which is another doore of hope: when <hi>Manoah</hi> was afraid, &amp; thought that he ſhould die, becauſe that he had ſeen God, his wife doth comfort him, ſaying, <hi>If the Lord were pleaſed to kill us, he would</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judg. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3. 23.</note> 
               <hi>not have received a burnt offering, and a meat offering at our hands, neither would he have ſhewed us all theſe things, neither would hee have told us ſuch things as theſe, q. d.</hi> Man, what talkeſt thou of dying, ſo long as God is accepting.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The doore of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> 7. The foundations that are laid for a glorious Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: God hath raiſed up glorious workmen, who have carried
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:112503:30"/> out much of the old rubbiſh, cleared in gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t meaſure the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, and brought in place many good materials, tending to the beautifying of the Church, I dare ſay, that is laid in, which all helliſh oppoſition ſhall never be able to overthrow.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The doore of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> 8. The zeale and courage of the worthies aſſembled in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament: they are men ſo raiſed up in their ſpirits, and ſo united among themſelves, that no threates, or diſcouragements can daunt or put them off from their working; they work unwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riably, and couragiouſly, notwithſtanding all that they doe, and all that is done againſt them, they ſhine in their faces, ſo that heaven may appeare to own and comfort them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The doore of oppoſition.</note> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> 9. The inſolencies of enemies againſt the proceedings of the Parliament: when enemies of Religion are high flowne, and dare to fight againſt Parliaments, againſt Lawes, againſt Chriſtians, and againſt all that is called God, it is an evidence that they are under the curſe, and nigh unto ruine, their great braggings and baſe attempts muſt not deſpaire our ſpirits, no man ever proſpered or prevailed, that malitiouſly and deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately did ſet himſelfe againſt the Parliament, it is that ſtone, which whoſoever thinkes to remove, he ſhall be cruſhed by it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The doore of aſſiſtance.</note> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> 10. The Earths helping of the woman: We have ſeen the ſpirits of men in all places raiſed up, to come to aſſiſt the cauſe of Jeſus Chriſt, help hath come in to the Worthies in an unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected way, even from ſuch who have been thought to have no Religion, men of all ſorts have combined themſelves to defend Religion, the Lawes of the Land, the Liberties of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, and the Priviledges of Parliaments, hating and abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the courſes which are deſtructive to the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The doore of heaven.</note> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> 11. The conſtantneſſe, and unchangeableneſſe of God in his working for us, and aſſiſting of us: England may ſet up <hi>Samuels</hi> Stone, which was called <hi>Eben-Ezer,</hi> that is, <hi>Hitherto</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 7. 12.</note> 
               <hi>hath the Lord helped us:</hi> Certainly, <hi>there hath been the leaſt of man, and the moſt of God diſcovered in the late paſſages, that ever Nation beheld,</hi> yea, and our God is conſtant with us, though men and times change, yet God changeth not, you ſhall finde him in his old place, even when men, <hi>great men and falſe hearted men,</hi> who have deceived the Kingdome in their truſt, doe ſlip their necks out of the coller, and ſeem to turn <hi>Renegadoes.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:112503:31"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The doore of Achor.</note> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> 12. We are in the valley of <hi>Achor:</hi> Now is the day and time of conſternation and trouble, the tyde is at higheſt, the night is at darkeſt, our miſeries are ſuch as threaten nothing but ruine and deſtruction unto us, and therefo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e we may hope, I ſay that our very miſeries may be unto us a doore of hope:<note place="margin">Pſal. 56. 3. Pſal. 130. 1.</note> 
               <hi>What time I am afraid, I will truſt in thee:</hi> and <hi>Out of the deepes have I cryed unto thee, O Lord: Davids</hi> ſearing times were his beleeving times, and his dangerous times were his praying times; our greateſt dangers cannot put us beyond our hopes: The Athenians when they were in great danger at Sea, were wont to caſt out that great Anchor which they called the holy Anchor.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sacram anchoram ſolvere dicimur qu ando ad extremum praeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinm</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eraſmi Adaz. ex Lucia.</note> 
               <hi>confugimus:</hi> If the Heathens were not without hope in dangers on the Sea, ſhall Chriſtians (think you) be leſt without hope? nay, ſo long as Chriſtians have a God to look upon, and a promiſe to relie upon, they ſhall never faile of a doore of hope: it is not all the bluſtering in the North by great ones and Cavaliers, which can hinder God from ſetting up a doore of hope for his ſervants in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> Thirdly, let us live as men to whom a doore of hope is vouchſafed. 1. Be not diſtracted and diſtreſſed in your ſpirits by the change of things or times, and with the comming in of<note place="margin">4. Signes of ſuch who have a doore of hope. Pſal. 39 7.</note> more and greater troubles; let none of thoſe things diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage you, under all rumors of War, and approaches of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſay, <hi>And now Lord what wait I for? truly my hope is even in thee:</hi> ſpeake out, yet God is good to Iſrael <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>, theſe things will not endure an age <note n="b" place="margin">N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ia eſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>: It is but a ſhowre that will ſoone paſſe over. 3. Look for more than you have in hand, your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent mercies are not all your mercies, there is much more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde, God hath raiſed up the hearts of his, to expect great and wonderfull things: and as we muſt be thankfull for what is done, ſo we muſt wait upon God for that which is yet to bee done, reputing all our receipts to be ſo many pledges and pawnes of further and future good. 3. Goe on with your work, you may not expect great things, and caſt off duty: our hope for mercy and deliverance will make us induſtrious and endeavouring in our places to praiſe and pleaſe God in all
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:112503:31"/> things. 4. Puzzle not your ſelves with diſorderly plots, do not ſeeke to piece heaven and earth, and to compound humane and divine helpes, know what man cannot, God can, and will doe, and that things many times are better for us in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, then in our own hands: We cannot thinke of, or finde out alwayes the beſt meanes to do our ſelves or the Kingdome good: Fleſh and blood will be often at a ſtand in its advice.</p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>4</label> Fourthly, learne to keep open the doore of your hope;</p>
            <p>To this end:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Make not your thoughts the meaſure of Gods ſtrength;<note place="margin">Ubi deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nit hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manum, ibiinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit divinum au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xilium.</note> where humane help faileth, there divine help beginneth, if it be a work that man can doe, it is not a work fit for God to do.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Make God, who is the God of nature, the orderer and over-ruler of all ſecond cauſes, and outward impediments, all<note place="margin">6. Wayes of keeping open the doore of hope.</note> things muſt ſtoop to God, and that in an inſtant, oh how ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly can God dry up, and divide the Sea? how wonderfully can he command the hearts of Kings? and how quickly can he turne into fooliſhneſſe the councells of all <hi>Achitophels?</hi> All things are too weak to fruſtrate Gods purpoſes and promiſes: Clouds and ſtormes may be in the ayre, but not in the higheſt heaven, the waters may carry down a planke, but the rocke remaines ſtill, nothing can hinder the Almighty God, he hath the <hi>Malignant party</hi> under his command, as much as he had <hi>Rabſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Keep open the doore of heaven, ceaſe not praying day and night: if we keep up our ſpirits in prayer, the doore of our hopes will be kept open.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Advance the grace of faith to liberty of working: as the promiſe goes before faith, ſo faith goes before hope, the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of good ariſeth out of an apprehenſion and perſwaſion of good; the truth is, that hope doth ſo depend <hi>ex judicio fidei,</hi> that if men beleeve not, they ſhall not hope, even as the inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours doe move at the motion of the Superiours, ſo hope riſeth, is furthered and continued in its working by faith: Well then, would you keep open the doore of hope, exalt faith, and let it act into the promiſes, whileſt faith is feeding and faſtning it ſelfe upon the promiſes, a man ſhall have hope in the darkeſt night, as well as in the lighteſt day.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:112503:32"/>5. Provoke not God by ſinning: There is nothing but ſin which can ſhut up the doore of our hopes, if that at ſuch times as theſe, wherein God is promiſing, and we are expecting mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, we ſhall be an unreformed people, and diſcover our ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities: what can God do leſſe then to ſhut the doore againe, ſaying, I would have cured and reformed England, yea, I gave them faire hopes for the ſame, but loe her inhabitants are proud and idle, they ſweare, and whore, and lie, and ſteale, and are drunken, and therefore now I will not give them my mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and grace.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Be prudent in ſeeking the publique Reformation; Let every man keep his ſtanding, and move to his owne Orbe: Though all <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ſhould have publique ſpirits, yet they have not publique places, if men will be diſcreet and quiet, things will be beſt amended, indiſcretion may ſhut the doore aſter then moſt men are aware of: Thinke of theſe things, warme your ſpirits by them, confer of them as you ride home from the Market, and ſay to your friends and acquaintance, <hi>Yet there is hope in Iſrael, even in England.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:112503:32"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
